<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Ioseph a poem. VVritten by Sir Thomas Salusbury, Barronet, late of the Inner Temple.</title>
            <title>Life of Joseph</title>
            <author>Salusbury, Thomas, Sir, d. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851738</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1005:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Ioseph a poem. VVritten by Sir Thomas Salusbury, Barronet, late of the Inner Temple.</title>
                  <title>Life of Joseph</title>
                  <author>Salusbury, Thomas, Sir, d. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Roger Ball, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Golden Anchor in the Strand, neere Temple-Barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of: The life of Joseph.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joseph --  (Son of Jacob) --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF IOSEPH: A POEM.</p>
            <p>VVritten by Sir <hi>Thomas Salusbury,</hi> Barronet, late of the Inner Temple.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> for <hi>Roger Ball,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Golden Anchor in the Strand, neere Temple-Barre, 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:2"/>
            <p>PErlegi hunc librum, cui titulus (<hi>the life of</hi> Joſeph, &amp;c.) in quo nihil reperio ſanae fidei, aut bonis moribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. Weeks,</hi> Epiſ. <hi>Lond.</hi> Cap. domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:2"/>
            <head>TO MY HONOVRED Grand-mother, the LADY <hi>Middleton,</hi> Late Wife to the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> Knight and <hi>Alderman,</hi> ſomtimes <hi>Major</hi> of the City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honour'd Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have now unto your Ladiſhips acceptance, and the worlds cenſure, adventured theſe unripe fruits of a forced Muſe;
<pb facs="tcp:17029:3"/> which if you ſhall accept (as they are truly meant) in witneſſe how ready an obſerver I am of your commands, I ſhall (arming my ſelf with patience and humility the hand-maids of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) humbly ſubmit and patiently reſolve to bear all juſt blame the world may lay upon my rudenes (however your Ladiſhip will be able to excuſe) the betraying ſo worthy a ſubject to ſo weake a verſe. It ſhall ſuffice mee that the world take notice, that my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours are only ambitious, to ſatisfie the ingagements, whereby your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips love hath obliged me unto you: by none ſo paraleld as by that of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Grand-children: who made <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> (as <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Simeon</hi>) his owne. The like from my youth hath beene your care and tenderneſſe over me, which I have no
<pb facs="tcp:17029:3"/> way to requite but by my thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reſpect and obedience to your commands. In obſervance whereof I commend this Poem to your patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and my ſelf to do you ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your dutifull Grand-child,</hi> Thomas Salusbury.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:4"/>
            <head>To the Noble Barronnet, Sir THOMAS SALUSBURY, upon his <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi> Muſt commend thy judgement, that could chuſe</l>
            <l>A ſubject, ſo well fitted to thy Muſe;</l>
            <l>That they adorne each other; that they ſhare</l>
            <l>In equall glory: that thy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dare</l>
            <l>(And without danger) thus himſelfe expoſe</l>
            <l>To th' envy of his friends, as well as foes,</l>
            <l>And (Confident of thy iuſt merit) ſlight</l>
            <l>His Brethrens malice, and the <hi>Iſmaelite.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nay, thinke his time in Servitude well ſpent,</l>
            <l>Since now he is become thy Argument.</l>
            <l>Whereby he is advanced farre above</l>
            <l>What <hi>Aegypt</hi> could affoord, or <hi>Pharoh's</hi> love.</l>
            <l>So happily thou haſt expreſt his worth,</l>
            <l>And in ſuch lively colours ſet him forth,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Putiphars</hi> wife is blameleſſe: all confeſſe</l>
            <l>There was no guilt in her laſciviouſneſſe.</l>
            <l>And had that love ſicke Lady us'd the Arte</l>
            <l>Which thy well languag'd Courtſhip doth impart</l>
            <l>Vnto her in this ſtory: the aſſault</l>
            <l>Had conquer'd <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and excus'd the fault;</l>
            <l>The charme had beene ſo forcible, that he</l>
            <l>Muſt with his Cloake, quit his humanity:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:5"/>
            <l>Or condiſcend, or had his Miſtreſſe read</l>
            <l>This Poem; and obſerv'd how thou doſt plead</l>
            <l>For thy chaſte <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> in as chaſte a rime,</l>
            <l>In Deteſtation of ſo foule a Crime.</l>
            <l>She had abhor'd her ſelfe, and lou'd him more</l>
            <l>For's vertue now, then for his face before.</l>
            <l>So potent is thy verſe: it doth ſuppreſſe</l>
            <l>And quench all looſer flames of wantonneſſe;</l>
            <l>And kindle in our breaſts and cold deſires,</l>
            <l>New heate reviv'd by thy <hi>Promethean</hi> fires.</l>
            <l>Be that thy ſole reward, and doe not weigh</l>
            <l>The Cenſure of the world. Some will inveigh,</l>
            <l>Some will commend: but moſt proclaime by me,</l>
            <l>They envy <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that detract from thee.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. LL. Dr. I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:5"/>
            <head>To my honoured friend, Sir <hi>Thomas Salusbury,</hi> my opinion of his <hi>IOSEPH.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>AS <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Brethrens ſheaves did all obay</l>
            <l>Young <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſtraite and lofty ſheafe, ſo may</l>
            <l>All other Poets not alone rehearſe</l>
            <l>Thy prayſes, but doe homage to thy verſe.</l>
            <l>Not blaſted with thoſe Criticks breaths, who ſpit</l>
            <l>Malice: and throw thy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the pit</l>
            <l>Of Envy; making their dull braines the Well</l>
            <l>To drowne thy fame, whoſe ſhallow pates excell</l>
            <l>Poore <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Well for emptineſſe: the pit</l>
            <l>Wanted not waters, as their heads doe wit.</l>
            <l>Some will be apt to ſay (when firſt 'tis knowne,</l>
            <l>Thy Muſe doth bud) the Roſe is over-blowne,</l>
            <l>The ſubject's ſtale: it is not good to ſee</l>
            <l>Men play and dally with Divinity.</l>
            <l>Thus will thoſe Critickes talke, were but thy vaine</l>
            <l>Such as deſcended from a love-ſicke braine.</l>
            <l>O that were rare, and excellent! how fine</l>
            <l>Were thoſe thy verſes, were they not divine?</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:6"/>
            <l>When e're thy <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> ſold unto ſuch wights,</l>
            <l>There's <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſold unto the <hi>Iſmaelites.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But ſince thy Muſe of Chaſtity doth ſing,</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> may finde favour with the King.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Bayly, artium Magiſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:6"/>
            <l>IF newes of <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> death o're <hi>Iacob</hi> have</l>
            <l>Such forch, to bring his gray haires to the grave</l>
            <l>With ſorrow, ſure with joy my tidings muſt</l>
            <l>As powerfull be, to raiſe him from the duſt:</l>
            <l>Then <hi>Iacob</hi> riſe and know thy darling Sonne</l>
            <l>Is yet alive; his glory but begunne,</l>
            <l>Then when thou left'ſt him was: he now is more</l>
            <l>A Favourite, then e're he was before.</l>
            <l>Not <hi>Pharoh's</hi> ſelfe, nor all the Sonnes of <hi>Nile</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Have ſo much grac'd him as thy lofty ſtile,</l>
            <l>My friend hath done: he in thy verſe ſhall be</l>
            <l>Ev'n as in heav'n, above Mortalitie.</l>
            <l>O how divin's thy Muſe then that can bleſſe,</l>
            <l>And adde to Saints departed happiveſſe.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Salusbury, Sen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:7"/>
            <head>In Authorem, &amp; Librum.</head>
            <l>I Know it's worth yet will I not commend</l>
            <l>Thy Book, I do not love to prayſe my friend</l>
            <l>Unleſſe ſome foule Detraction I ſhould heare,</l>
            <l>Of him, or his; elſe to commend him were</l>
            <l>In friendſhip as abſurd; as ſhould I write</l>
            <l>Strong Arguments to prove that ſnow is white.</l>
            <l>Nor will I yet admire thy work, to mee</l>
            <l>It is a thing not ſtrange at all to ſee,</l>
            <l>That what thou doſt is excellent I know,</l>
            <l>Thy ſelf art abſolute, and thy works are ſo:</l>
            <l>Yet mayſt thou meet ſome Cenſurers too unkind,</l>
            <l>But pity them, who puniſhment ſhall find</l>
            <l>Enough in their own errour: they condemne</l>
            <l>Thy work, whilſt better judgments laugh at them.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Salusbury Iun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:7"/>
            <head>To my ever honour'd Sir <hi>T.</hi> S. Barronet, upon his <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SO the ſweet ſinger did of <hi>Iſrael</hi> uſe,</l>
               <l>In holy Layes to exerciſe his Muſe:</l>
               <l>Prayſing his God, for wonders in the Land</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Egypt</hi> by his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> hand.</l>
               <l>Then with Gods mercies ſweetly cloſing there,</l>
               <l>The ſoule at once he raviſh't, and the ear.</l>
               <l>But ſo long ſince is that, that there be thoſe,</l>
               <l>Make ſcruple yet whether in Verſe or Proſe,</l>
               <l>The Prophet wrote, as if a meaſur'd line</l>
               <l>Were more unfit to treat of things divine.</l>
               <l>Such heretiques of Poetry by chance,</l>
               <l>Will in their cenſure ſhew their ignorance</l>
               <l>Of this thy labours worth, when they ſhall hold</l>
               <l>It as a fruitleſſe work, if not a bold:</l>
               <l>Deeming the ſacred flames that thus inſpire</l>
               <l>Thy breſts with holy raptures, a ſtrange fire.</l>
               <l>And count thee as prophane, that dar'ſt rehearſe,</l>
               <l>The majeſtie of Scripture in a Verſe.</l>
               <l>Whilſt men of abler judgments, that deſcry</l>
               <l>This laſt worſt ages curious nicety</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:17029:8"/>
               <l>Such, that Gods ſacred word, the heavenly bread</l>
               <l>Of life, by moſt is dully reliſhed,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe in oyle or honey dipt, they know,</l>
               <l>He whom the holy Ghoſts firſt penman ſo</l>
               <l>Extolled, as the type of Chriſt, and ſquare</l>
               <l>Of vertues, for all graces ſingular;</l>
               <l>Had ſlept the ſubiect of our coy neglect,</l>
               <l>As buried in the Scribes grave dialect:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ioſephs</hi> goodneſſe, ſuch, ſome few alone</l>
               <l>Profeſſors, and Preciſians had knowne;</l>
               <l>Had not thy bounteous Muſe thus ſet him forth</l>
               <l>In faſhionable garbe, to ſpeake his worth</l>
               <l>In moderne tone; now by thy helpe he may</l>
               <l>Converſe with Courtiers, in a Coat as gay</l>
               <l>As er'ſt his Father made him; he may kiſſe</l>
               <l>Each coyer Ladies hand, nor can he miſſe</l>
               <l>Admiſsion, or audience to tell</l>
               <l>His ſtory to the beſt, or worſt; ſo well</l>
               <l>He charmes attention: by his ſweet and ſmooth</l>
               <l>Expreſsions, ſo pathetically ſoothes</l>
               <l>His hearers to receive his ſugred pils,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt at their raviſh't eares and eyes he inſtils</l>
               <l>His modeſty into their ſoules; and ſo</l>
               <l>Doth <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> ſtory told 'mongſt high and low,</l>
               <l>With greater efficacy, vertue teach,</l>
               <l>By's paterne, then beſt precepts we can preach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In briefe, I iudge thy Poem to be ſuch,</l>
               <l>So good, ſo pleaſant, that I dare avouch,</l>
               <l>The reader that no profit reapes by it,</l>
               <l>Or pleaſure, hath nor piety, nor wit.</l>
               <l>Hold on this godly courſe, thy talent ſpend</l>
               <l>By tickling thus our eares, our heart; to mend.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:17029:8"/>
               <l>And when thy budding Springs, ſpare houres bring forth</l>
               <l>Such fruit, how great ſhall be thy harveſts worth,</l>
               <l>When thy green youth could ſo exactly trace</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Ioſephs'</hi> perfect wayes; well may thy grace</l>
               <l>In riper yeares, as his recorded be,</l>
               <l>A Mappe of vertues to poſterity.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. LL. artium Magiſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:9"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Author unknown, and his <hi>IOSEPH.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F fitneſſe be a Poems excellence,</l>
            <l>When to the Subject, Stile combines with ſenſe,</l>
            <l>Where lofty matter, lofty lines doe ſwell,</l>
            <l>Where lowly Theames, low words doe paralell;</l>
            <l>When under ſhadowed phraſe, doth couched lye</l>
            <l>Sometimes a ſmile, ſometimes a myſtery:</l>
            <l>Still keeping chaſte to chaſte, and high to high,</l>
            <l>Gloſſing cloſe ſecrets ſtill with ſecreſie.</l>
            <l>Then top of wit and maſterpiece of skill,</l>
            <l>I here diſcover from a knightly quill.</l>
            <l>For in theſe ſheets here ſwadled up, I ſpi'd</l>
            <l>The new borne <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from his duſt reviv'd:</l>
            <l>And from the Preſſes reaking leaden wombe,</l>
            <l>I ſaw ſo faire an Hebrew Of-ſpring come,</l>
            <l>So modeſt, chaſte, ſo <hi>Ioſeph</hi>-like it ſeem'd,</l>
            <l>As if againe faire <hi>Rachels</hi> wombe had teem'd.</l>
            <l>And h'an't you read, how <hi>Ioſephs</hi> growing mite</l>
            <l>(By faire degrees) raiſe him a favourite.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:17029:10"/>
            <l>So doth he here in ſuch brave order riſe,</l>
            <l>As may indeare him to his <hi>Pharoh's</hi> eyes.</l>
            <l>Next, as the reſt their flagging tops did bend</l>
            <l>To <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Sheafe, ſtill mounting up an end;</l>
            <l>So you fond Bards (like their ungrounded ſheaves)</l>
            <l>To this green Laurell, vaile your ſapleſſe Reaves.</l>
            <l>Blaſt not his worthy fame, here newly blowne,</l>
            <l>But learne to mend the ruines of your owne.</l>
            <l>Loe here your Preſident, where you may ſee</l>
            <l>How farre divine wit, paſſeth Surquedree.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17029:10"/>
            <head>THE DREAMER, OR The firſt Chapter of <hi>Ioſeph. GEN. the 37.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>JOSEPH,</hi> a Sheep-heard, doth conſort</l>
               <l>With's brethren; tel's their ill report:</l>
               <l>His Father loves him in extreames,</l>
               <l>For which he's hated, and his dreames:</l>
               <l>He's thrown into the pit, and ſold</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> for gold,</l>
               <l>Who to <hi>Aegypt</hi> having brought him,</l>
               <l>The ſecond time a Courtier bought him.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, alwaies juſt, begins in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed,</l>
               <l>To ratifie his Promiſe with his Deed;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> holds faſt, and hath by this time well</l>
               <l>Deſerv'd the happy name of <hi>Izrael:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 31.24.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Angell now would part, he (though diſable,</l>
               <l>His thigh disjoynted, undefatigable)</l>
               <l>Tugs for his bleſſing; as when heretofore,</l>
               <l>For his lo'vd <hi>Rachel,</hi> he ſerv'd ſev'n yeers more:</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17029:11"/>
               <l>Yong <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s joyfull Mother now (with whom,</l>
               <l>A good portent!) God op'd her barren womb,</l>
               <l>Took from her, her reproach; <hi>Iſrael</hi> and ſhe,</l>
               <l>Equally bleſt by importunity:</l>
               <l>He, for a bleſſing; She, for one to bleſſe;</l>
               <l>Both earneſt ſutors, both with like ſucceſſe.</l>
               <l>Hence for all croſſes arm'd, and black deſpayr,</l>
               <l>Learn; GOD himſelf is overcom by prayr:</l>
               <l>If thou as earneſt be in ſeeking, as</l>
               <l>Un-tyred <hi>Izrael</hi> and his <hi>Rachel</hi> was:</l>
               <l>Who now, above the reſt, doe love this boy,</l>
               <l>As one not gotten in the common way,</l>
               <l>But as a ſigne of God's continued love,</l>
               <l>A prayr-gain'd childe immediat from above:</l>
               <l>As, when the minde of Man ſome good conceives</l>
               <l>His hopes dare ſcarce attempt, and yet receives;</l>
               <l>In like degree he loves it (now it is)</l>
               <l>As if, he durſt, he could have wiſh't it his:</l>
               <l>Or, as things held in long ſuſpence before</l>
               <l>They're granted us, we ever prize them more</l>
               <l>Then eaſier purchaſes; As we prefer</l>
               <l>Miraculous, before things commoner:</l>
               <l>So they their <hi>Joſeph,</hi> with whom God did bleſſe</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s age, and <hi>Rachel</hi>'s barrenneſſe;</l>
               <l>It was enough (he was her ſonne) to move,</l>
               <l>His father, to a more then uſuall love.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A coate, of many curious colours wrought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He made for him;</hi> Joſeph <hi>was all his thought;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> was his delight; but yet ſo far</l>
               <l>As hopefull children to wiſe parents are,</l>
               <l>He made no fondling of him; he could brooke</l>
               <l>The lov'd child's abſence; nor was griev'd to looke</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17029:11"/>
               <l>Upon his labors; nor was <hi>Joſeph</hi> fed</l>
               <l>With finer meates, nor warm'd a ſofter bed</l>
               <l>With longer priviledge, nor was he ſpar'd</l>
               <l>From any paines wherein his brethren ſhar'd,</l>
               <l>Nor groan'd he for his burthen, nor did grumble,</l>
               <l>But with prompt will, and an obedience humble,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strove to performe his taske; He went to keepe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(With</hi> Bilhah's <hi>and with</hi> Zilpah's <hi>ſons) the ſheepe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And whilſt his brethren he did thus conſort,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He brought his father home their ill-report,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who joy'd, they griev'd, ſo yong a one to ſee</l>
               <l>Deteſt, and to detect their infamie:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Jacob</hi> who too wiſe, above the reſt</l>
               <l>Fondly to love one, and for nothing beſt</l>
               <l>At leaſt to ſhew it; yet he muſt approve</l>
               <l>And cheriſh virtue, with increaſe of love;</l>
               <l>Which now he cannot hide, being ſwel'd as high</l>
               <l>As <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s merits; Virtue firſt may lie</l>
               <l>Or Truth conceal'd, or the fel-brethrens hate,</l>
               <l>Ere his affection, now grown paſſionate.</l>
               <l>And they (who for a teltale heretofore,</l>
               <l>Now as their fathers-fondling) hate him more:</l>
               <l>Beſides, nought renders one to envious hearts</l>
               <l>More deſpicable then excelling parts;</l>
               <l>So, nought more then his virtue did incenſe</l>
               <l>His brethren's rage; his fault was Innocence.</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Jacob</hi>'s quarell was, ſuch <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s fate,</l>
               <l>As 'twere to inherit thus his brethrens hate:</l>
               <l>The Fathers life, one <hi>Eſau</hi>'s hate purſu'de;</l>
               <l>The Son was troubled with a multitude:</l>
               <l>He got the bleſſing from them, and they ſpight</l>
               <l>Him, now, their God's, and father's favorite.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17029:12"/>
               <l>And where this helliſh fury once is bred</l>
               <l>Of brethrens diſcord, there 'tis eas'ly fed</l>
               <l>By ev'ry new occaſion; <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s minde</l>
               <l>Was then inlightned, when his body blinde</l>
               <l>With drowzie reſt, in heavie ſleep he wink't;</l>
               <l>Yet ſaw and learn't, by a divine inſtinct,</l>
               <l>Moſt ſtrange events (ſuch alwayes are the waies</l>
               <l>Whereby God was reveal'd in following daies</l>
               <l>Unto their of-ſpring) when, 'gainſt all extreams,</l>
               <l>Their age ſaw viſions, &amp; their youth dream'd dreams</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſephs</hi> first dreame.</note>
                  <hi>So</hi> Joſeph <hi>now; When as me thought all we</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Were binding ſheaves of Corne, i'th field, quoth he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto his brethren, that my ſheafe aroſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſtood upright i'th midſt, When loe all thoſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of yours ſtood round, and with reclined head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As in obeyſance, my ſheafe worſhipped.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Scarce had he ended, when they murmuring all,</l>
               <l>Some with a Soule like-troubled as when <hi>Saul</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the rais'd Prophet heard his ſudden doome,</l>
               <l>And the ſad ruin of his houſe to come:</l>
               <l>Some with a ſcorn; as when <hi>Goliah</hi> ſpide</l>
               <l>So weake a Champion come, t'afront his pride</l>
               <l>With ſtaffe and ſling; with like beleefe of fate</l>
               <l>Enſuing, they began to vent their hate.</l>
               <l>And are we born, fond-dreamer, to obey?</l>
               <l>Muſt we indeed thy vaſſalls be, cry'd they?</l>
               <l>Muſt we adore thine eyes, and ſeeke grace thence?</l>
               <l>Whom Time and Nature gave preheminence?</l>
               <l>What frantick pride tranſports thy fancy thus?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall ſuch a boy as thou reign over <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thus they ſwel'd to a more high contempt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of him, becauſe he told them what he dreampt:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17029:12"/>
               <l>Yet this informing Genius left him not,</l>
               <l>But newer fancies in his braine begot;</l>
               <l>Such, and of like preſage, which mindles he</l>
               <l>Of all their bitter flouts and mockery</l>
               <l>Freely vents out, ev'n to his fathers eare,</l>
               <l>Not caring though his envious brethren heare.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſecond dreame.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me thought the Sun and Moone (did mee adore)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And th'elev'n Stars, as did the ſheaves before,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quoth he, with like obeiſance:</hi> Now his Syre,</l>
               <l>In whoſe ag'd boſom rag'd th'un-uſual fire</l>
               <l>Of indignation, this relation mov'd</l>
               <l>Him in this ſort to check the childe he lov'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What haſt thou dreampt fond boy? What ſhall we all,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Father, Mother, and thy Brethren, fall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In reverence to thee?</hi> Truſt not theſe vaine</l>
               <l>And fond illuſions of an idle braine:</l>
               <l>Shall then that bleſſing leave me that hath gon</l>
               <l>Still an inſeparable companion</l>
               <l>Of comfort with me? That which <hi>Iſaac</hi> gave,</l>
               <l>And that which purchas'd I with lameneſſe have</l>
               <l>Of my touch't thigh, when all the night I ſtrove</l>
               <l>With heav'nly powers, diſcended from above,</l>
               <l>Till I obtain'd? And ſhall my name, which men</l>
               <l>Us'd ſacred, in their deepeſt Oaths, and when</l>
               <l>They ſpeake to any unbeleeving eare,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi>'s God they ſweare?</l>
               <l>Shall this name ſtoope to thine? Muſt thou indeede</l>
               <l>Be only bleſt of all the promis'd ſeede?</l>
               <l>Thus chek't he him; <hi>Yet, ner'e the leſſe, each part</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Joſeph's <hi>tale he treaſur'd in his heart;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So did his brethren too, though their intent</l>
               <l>From their good fathers was farre different:</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:17029:13"/>
               <l>They ſtore his ſayings up, as fuel fit</l>
               <l>To feed their-hel-bred fire and nouriſh it,</l>
               <l>Blown to too great a height already, by</l>
               <l>Him that firſt chang'd the warmth and purity</l>
               <l>Of fire, to ſcorching heate, that it might be</l>
               <l>A meete reward to perpetuitie</l>
               <l>For his demerits; who, thus damn'd to flames,</l>
               <l>To make all partners of his torture aimes</l>
               <l>Here and for ever, and to that end he</l>
               <l>Tormenteth ſome with burning jealouſie;</l>
               <l>Others, with flames of hate and rancorous ire</l>
               <l>Prepares as charcoales for eternall fire,</l>
               <l>'Mongſt all in generall (as they are inclin'd)</l>
               <l>He caſts theſe ſparks, which kindled once, a wind</l>
               <l>From any thing hee'l rayſe, to fan withall</l>
               <l>The heate more furious, not a word can fall</l>
               <l>From harmleſſe <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which not ſomthing hath</l>
               <l>That ads to his incenſed brethrens wrath</l>
               <l>By this time grown to ſuch a helliſh flame,</l>
               <l>That nothing but his blood can quench the ſame:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20</note>But God, that's True and Gracious, pitty takes</l>
               <l>Ev'n unto thouſands, for their fathers ſakes;</l>
               <l>Their Sins cannot old <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſervice blot,</l>
               <l>Nor may his oath to <hi>Abraham</hi> be forgot,</l>
               <l>But unto all their goods his love converts</l>
               <l>The ill meant ſpleene of their malicious hearts:</l>
               <l>Loe how to future times doth this foretell</l>
               <l>The childrens ſtubbornneſſe of <hi>Jſrael</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From their beginning; ag'd but one diſcent,</l>
               <l>Their plot is murther of the innocent;</l>
               <l>So miſchievous their minds, ſo bent on blood,</l>
               <l>They ſpar'd not thoſe that did or meant them good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17029:13"/>
               <l>'Twas early in the morn when they were gon</l>
               <l>Forth with their Fathers flocks, to feede upon</l>
               <l>The plaines of <hi>Sechem,</hi> where they not above</l>
               <l>A few ſhort houres had ſpent, when <hi>Jacob</hi>'s love</l>
               <l>Mov'd his deſire to know what had befell</l>
               <l>Them ſince their parting, whether all were well</l>
               <l>Amongſt their flocks and them, if they had found</l>
               <l>Good ſhades to reſt in, or good feeding ground</l>
               <l>There for their ſheep and heards, and thus inclinde</l>
               <l>He calls yong <hi>Joſeph</hi> to him, bids him finde</l>
               <l>His brethren out, where they in <hi>Sechem</hi> are,</l>
               <l>See them and bring me knowledge how they fare</l>
               <l>The youth is ſoon commanded, which he ſhewes</l>
               <l>In quick obedience, forth he gladly goes</l>
               <l>On this kind errand, to perform the will</l>
               <l>Of him that ſent him, never fearing ill</l>
               <l>Becauſe he meant no harm; So innocent</l>
               <l>Was his great Maſter from his Father ſent</l>
               <l>To their curſt Of-ſpring; who, not only bred</l>
               <l>From cruell loynes, but more experienced</l>
               <l>In blood and murther; having ſlayn ev'n all</l>
               <l>That came and would them to repentance call,</l>
               <l>So wicked as they are, they ſend t'his grave</l>
               <l>Him that brought peace to all, and came to ſave.</l>
               <l>Who with an unmov'd ſoule as cheerfull went</l>
               <l>To give his Fathers will accompliſhment</l>
               <l>Ev'n to the death, though hence the difference grew,</l>
               <l>He that his Fathers wiſedome was, fore-knew</l>
               <l>His danger, <hi>Joſeph</hi> went in little doubt</l>
               <l>Oth' ſad event to finde his brethren out</l>
               <l>And comes by this to <hi>Sechem,</hi> cals and cries</l>
               <l>Aloud upon them, but there's none replies</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17029:14"/>
               <l>Untill as in their queſt he roving ran</l>
               <l>Thus through the ſpacious fields, he met a man,</l>
               <l>Who finding him, demanded what might be</l>
               <l>The cauſe of his ſo buſie ſearch; quoth he</l>
               <l>I ſeek my brethren Sir, can you I pray</l>
               <l>Direct my wandring ſteps, or tell where they</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have led their flocks; I have to find them out,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Traverſt the vale of</hi> Hebron <hi>and about</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The plaines of</hi> Sechem <hi>runne with fruitleſſe ſpeed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Meeting with none could tell me where they feed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No (quoth the man) then in good time I may</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give thee ſome eaſe at laſt: I heard them ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let us to</hi> Dothan <hi>hence;</hi> Scarce had he ſaid</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dothan,</hi> when <hi>Joſeph</hi> but to thank him ſtaid,</l>
               <l>Then with much haſte, making this news his guide,</l>
               <l>Poſts after them, whom when from far they ſpide,</l>
               <l>Their colours chang'd, and their diſtracted blood</l>
               <l>Eb'd to their hearts, and ſtreight guſh't like a flood</l>
               <l>Into their face and eys, and glowing there,</l>
               <l>Made their long carried coales in flames appeare:</l>
               <l>And then a murmur doth amongſt them runne,</l>
               <l>Like the winds ſtrugling ere the ſtorm's begunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When the foure Elements aſſembled are</l>
               <l>From all the corners of the Earth to warre</l>
               <l>In ſome great Tempeſt, when the Ayre and Fire</l>
               <l>Againſt the Earth and ſwelling-Seas conſpire,</l>
               <l>Thunder's their trumpet, at whoſe noyſe they fall</l>
               <l>In a rude conflict mixt, and threaten all</l>
               <l>Their poore inhabitants; Lightnings would dry</l>
               <l>The Seas, and they to quench heav'ns fires do try,</l>
               <l>And hel's flames too, where having falne, they riſe</l>
               <l>With a new crotchet now to ſtrike the Skies.</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17029:14"/>
               <l>The earth and ayr mean while as 'twere diſſolv'd</l>
               <l>Into one ill mixt body, look, involv'd.</l>
               <l>Thus altogether rude, and ſhapeleſſe as</l>
               <l>Old Chaos, ere the worlds creation was.</l>
               <l>Nothing but darkneſſe now, no light is found</l>
               <l>More then in wretched man, in paſſions drown'd:</l>
               <l>Reaſon extinguiſh't, man's a world compos'd</l>
               <l>Of all the elements which lye enclos'd</l>
               <l>In ſeverall humours, from them bred whence flow</l>
               <l>Our paſſions which being bound and ordered ſo</l>
               <l>By reaſon, as the world by light (the beſt</l>
               <l>And firſt of creatures, made to rule the reſt)</l>
               <l>Angels are in their kinde leſſe bleſt then we</l>
               <l>That images of our Creator be.</l>
               <l>But that curb break, and paſſions ruling, then</l>
               <l>No ſtorme, no Chaos, ſo deform'd as men.</l>
               <l>And thus with <hi>Joſeph's</hi> brethren 'twas that ſtood</l>
               <l>Now like ſo many <hi>Cains,</hi> in wait for's blood.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>See where yond dreamer comes (ſay they) let's kill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let's make an end of hm, and ſee what will</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Become of all his projects, and his viſions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His idle fancies, and fond aparitions,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for a good excuſe we can not miſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee'l ſay, Some beaſt devour'd him, true it is.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Moſt ſavage beaſts they were that thus did plot</l>
               <l>To ruine him, their rage conſidered not</l>
               <l>His fathers care who ſent, whoſe love him brought</l>
               <l>To hearken of their healths, this they nere thought.</l>
               <l>All ſeek his death but <hi>Ruben,</hi> who more milde</l>
               <l>Then were the reſt, labours to ſave the childe,</l>
               <l>The boy is yong, and childiſh, he in vain</l>
               <l>Urg'd, and for dreams deſerv's not to be ſlain.</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17029:15"/>
               <l>Then with his fathers weakneſſe intercedes,</l>
               <l>His years, and his great love to <hi>Joſeph</hi> pleads,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph's</hi> the ſtaffe, and prop of <hi>Iſraels</hi> age,</l>
               <l>Thus he perſiſts, but they ſtill deafe with rage,</l>
               <l>Give him no eare, his words can do no good:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which when he ſees, oh yet let's ſhed no blood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He cries, my brethren, I'le direct a way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To your revenge, and yet we will not ſlay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor lay our hands on him, not farre from hence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ith'deſert is a hollow hole, and thence</l>
               <l>Down to the bottome the diſcent ſo ſteep,</l>
               <l>That tis impoſſible he ere ſhould creep</l>
               <l>Again above ground, there's no water there,</l>
               <l>And tis ſo ſteep withall that none can heare</l>
               <l>His cryes, and if by chance he there be found,</l>
               <l>It may be ſaid, he fell into the ground.</l>
               <l>Then can it nere be told, we took his breath,</l>
               <l>Although indeed we left him to his death:</l>
               <l>None of his bloud can on our heads be laid:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For none of it we ſhed, all this he ſaid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To rid him from their hands, and if he might,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To bring him to their father home at night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At laſt more pacified, they take for ſence</l>
               <l>His words; and give him freer audience.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reuben,</hi> ſay they, ſpeaks truth, then let's not ſtrive,</l>
               <l>We will not kill, but bury him alive.</l>
               <l>Their plot concluded on, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> come,</l>
               <l>They fall upon him altogether: ſome</l>
               <l>Rip off his many colour'd coat (the ſigne</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Jacobs</hi> love) others make faſt a line</l>
               <l>About his tender waſte, and ripping thence</l>
               <l>All but his ſhirt, white like his innocence,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17029:15"/>
               <l>They hale him forwards, whilſt his grief, and fears,</l>
               <l>Can vent it ſelf in nothing, but in tears:</l>
               <l>They will not heare him ſpeak, nor are they mov'd,</l>
               <l>Nor once conſider'd how their father lov'd</l>
               <l>Thoſe blubber'd eyes; nor what hold grief would take</l>
               <l>On his gray hairs, for his loſt <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſake:</l>
               <l>Mindleſſe of this, with other thoughts then whet</l>
               <l>Their fury on, and more on edge did ſet</l>
               <l>Their vengeance, being by this come to the pit,</l>
               <l>They rudely take and caſt him into it:</l>
               <l>And in the ground they bury (O vild deed)</l>
               <l>Gods promiſe, and the hopes of <hi>Iſacque's</hi> ſeed.</l>
               <l>But ſee his power, that from the looſe ſtones can,</l>
               <l>Or looſer duſt, raiſe <hi>Abraham</hi> ſonnes, made man</l>
               <l>Of nought, can cauſe new quickned bodies come</l>
               <l>From the graves barren, and unfruitfull wombe.</l>
               <l>He that ſhall make all deeps, and ſeas at laſt,</l>
               <l>Their dead from forth their ſilent manſions caſt,</l>
               <l>That power can <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſeed ſo deeply ſowne,</l>
               <l>Cauſe ſprouting thence, to flouriſh in a throne.</l>
               <l>Ev'n he that puls the mighty from their ſeat,</l>
               <l>Shall make the loweſt higheſt, <hi>Joſeph</hi> great,</l>
               <l>Who left thus deep, now to his deeper thoughts,</l>
               <l>More then his own fate, wails his brethrens faults,</l>
               <l>Thinks on their impious rage, and what a curſe</l>
               <l>Muſt follow their offence, this griev'd him worſe</l>
               <l>Then his own ſuffrings, they mean while the feat</l>
               <l>Long plotted on perform'd, ſate down to eat</l>
               <l>On th'earths green carpet, but what ere their food,</l>
               <l>I dare preſume, their cheer was not ſo good,</l>
               <l>It cannot be the guilt of their offence</l>
               <l>Could ſit ſo light upon their conſcience.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17029:16"/>
               <l>Some anxious thoughts of their great God diſpleas'd</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Joſeph</hi> left to cold, and hunger, ſeiſed</l>
               <l>Sometimes upon them all, as there they led</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It ſeems they mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d, for lo they lift their head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And looking round, behold upon the ſight</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of certain Merchants, that were</hi> Iſhmaelites,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe camels loden (towards Aegypt bent)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With balme, and mirrh, and ſpice, from</hi> Gilead <hi>went<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>Judah <hi>cries out, what will it do us good</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To kill our brother, and conceal his bloud?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He is our brother, and our fleſh, 'twere well</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We layd no hands upon him, let us ſell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him rather to you Merchants, and being ſold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We are reveng'd, and our reward is gold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſaying pleas'd them all, and up they roſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Whilſt abſent</hi> Reuben <hi>nothing of it knows;)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And coming to the pit, caſt in a rope</l>
               <l>To hale up weeping <hi>Joſeph,</hi> now in hope</l>
               <l>Some pity came upon them, when he found</l>
               <l>Worſe miſchiefs gaping for him then the ground,</l>
               <l>He in the narrow confines of the cave</l>
               <l>Was King, there being none elſe, but now's a ſlave,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For th'</hi> Iſhmaelites <hi>being come, to them they brought him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who having lookt upon, and lik't him, bought him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For twenty ſilver peeces, a good rate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judas</hi> but thirty for his Maſter ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> thou highly valued art to riſe</l>
               <l>Within ten peeces of thy Saviours price,</l>
               <l>Thy brethren I'm aſſur'd, thought 'twas good gain</l>
               <l>To have revenge and ſilver for their pain.</l>
               <l>Two pieces ev'ry man, but now th'art gone</l>
               <l>A cloak to hide their fault, they think upon,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17029:16"/>
               <l>And here the worſt of all their malice noat,</l>
               <l>Their infamy, they cover, with thy coat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gods finger's in't, a ramme's for <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſlain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A kid for</hi> Joſeph, <hi>with whoſe blood they ſtain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His colour'd rayment, mean while to the pit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reuben <hi>makes haſte, and being come to it</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bows him there down, and whiſpers, brother riſe,</l>
               <l>I come to free thee from the cruelties</l>
               <l>Of them that hate thee, as from being ſlain</l>
               <l>I ſav'd, ſo now Ile bring thee home again</l>
               <l>Unto thy father: but when none replyes</l>
               <l>He doubts, and louder, and yet louder cryes:</l>
               <l>At laſt, with out-ſtretcht throat, he lifts his voyce,</l>
               <l>So have I often heard the climbing noyſe</l>
               <l>Of ſome exact Muſitian that begins</l>
               <l>So low, 'yould ſcarce beleeve he toucht the ſtrings:</l>
               <l>Then by degrees mounts to a tone ſo high</l>
               <l>That each eare tingles as in ſympathy,</l>
               <l>Or like the tune oth'winde, that calmly blows</l>
               <l>At firſt, then ſwels, and by degrees it grows</l>
               <l>Higher, and higher yet, and is at laſt</l>
               <l>Able to deafe the hearers, ev'ry blaſt:</l>
               <l>Such and ſo fruitleſſe, is th'exalted voyce</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Reuben</hi> now he hears no anſwring noyſe</l>
               <l>But his own eccho, willingly beguil'd,</l>
               <l>He takes that as an anſwer from the childe,</l>
               <l>And cals again, till reaſon makes him know</l>
               <l>It is not, though (God wot) he wiſh it ſo.</l>
               <l>He finds his error, and with tears laments</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His brothers loſſe, then paſſionatly rents</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His cloaths, and with redoubled haſte he makes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>After his brethren, whom he over-takes,</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17029:17"/>
               <l>Firſt with lamenting voyce, which to them cries,</l>
               <l>And coming near with teare-bedewed eyes,</l>
               <l>Joſeph <hi>is gone, what ſhall become of me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He was not in the pit, then farewell he,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They all replide, we need not fear his ſpight:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now, to bring home t'our father tales at night,</l>
               <l>You have not ſlain him then, good God defend;</l>
               <l>He from his brethren, this untimely end</l>
               <l>Should have, (quoth <hi>Reuben</hi>) no, be thou content,</l>
               <l>No violent hands we laid on him, yet ſent</l>
               <l>Him far enough from troubling us again,</l>
               <l>Nor is our quietneſſe the onely gain</l>
               <l>W'have made, nor yet our juſt revenge: but ſee,</l>
               <l>All this w'had for him, here's a ſhare for thee.</l>
               <l>Who when he ſaw no remedy, at laſt</l>
               <l>He purg'd himſelf oth'guilt, and forward paſt:</l>
               <l>Whilſt they applaud their doings and device,</l>
               <l>Th'ave found to blinde their fathers aged eyes,</l>
               <l>Who wiſht them blinde indeed, when they the coat</l>
               <l>Preſent unto him, and aſk him if he know't,</l>
               <l>He takes and views, and ſeeing it all ore</l>
               <l>Dipt in his beſt lov'd ſonnes ſuppoſed gore,</l>
               <l>He faine would not beleeve his eyes, on them</l>
               <l>He looks that brought it, then on it agen;</l>
               <l>He knows the work, and as he well may do,</l>
               <l>The making, and the curious colours too.</l>
               <l>So God the rain-bow cloath'd, which of his love</l>
               <l>And future pitty was the pledge, ſo 'bove</l>
               <l>His other brethren, this as a delight</l>
               <l>Did witneſſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> was in's fathers ſight.</l>
               <l>But here th'unhappy difference did prove,</l>
               <l>That ſhows Gods pitty, this mans pitty move.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17029:17"/>
               <l>Who having ſeen? a crimſon that out-ſhines</l>
               <l>The well preſt fruit of cluſter bearing vines,</l>
               <l>Or any thing of Nature well ſet by;</l>
               <l>To ſhadow forth the purple <hi>Syrian</hi> dye,</l>
               <l>Cloſe unto which another colour's layd,</l>
               <l>Pure as the modeſt bluſhes of a mayd,</l>
               <l>And ſundry other reds by a well taught,</l>
               <l>And curious needle-woman finely wrought</l>
               <l>Into one piller; in another's ſeen</l>
               <l>As many ſorts of well diſpoſed green,</l>
               <l>The next of yellow, and between them lay</l>
               <l>The fether of the prating Popingay,</l>
               <l>Flame colour then, and ſaffron you behold,</l>
               <l>Compared with the pleaſing hue of gold,</l>
               <l>And in like well mixt method you might finde</l>
               <l>Blacks, blues, and whites, divers of ev'ry kinde</l>
               <l>In ſeverall pillers wav'd, and neatly wrought</l>
               <l>Into one peece of ſtuffe, one curious coat:</l>
               <l>If I that artificiall work ſhould ſee</l>
               <l>Spoyl'd, and beſtain'd with bloud, 'twould pity me,</l>
               <l>How much is he mov'd then? that is perſwaded</l>
               <l>'Twas with his bloud, and death for whom he made it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>He that his paſſions wil expreſſe aright,</l>
               <l>Muſt be as he was in the ſelf ſame plight.</l>
               <l>His brows are cloudy, from his eyes it rains</l>
               <l>Salt ſhowres of tears, as t'were to waſh the ſtains</l>
               <l>From off the ſlubber'd coat, then with a groan,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that's ſpoil'd, hee'l likewiſe ſpoyl his own.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He rends his garments, and in ſack-cloth cloth's</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His aged loyns, then weeps afreſh and loaths</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All words of comfort,</hi> Joſeph <hi>thou art gone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Torn as my garment, bloudy as thine own,</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17029:18"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some evill beaſt, ſome bear, or lyon wilde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have fil'd their greedy panches with my childe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And now though all his ſonnes and daughters riſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To comfort him hee'l none: his big ſwoln eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Will take no truce from tears, they baniſh ſleep,</l>
               <l>And as 'twere made for nothing, but to weep.</l>
               <l>The day he in no other taſk out-wears,</l>
               <l>And all the night waters his couch with tears.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now thou art gone, what comfort can I have?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ile follow thee, my ſonne, into the grave,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With ſorrow Ile deſcend, thus grief prevail d</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ore the old man, and thus he long bewail'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The proſperous youth, who is by this time brought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Aegypt with thoſe Marchants, and there bought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> Putiphar, <hi>an officer by place</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chief Marſhal, and a man in</hi> Pharohs <hi>grace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17029:18"/>
            <head>THE PRISONER: OR, The ſecond Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 39.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>JOSEPH</hi> his Maſter puts in truſt,</l>
               <l>His Miſtreſſe tempts him to her luſt,</l>
               <l>Faire words, and threats, in vain ſhe uſde,</l>
               <l>Then in diſdaine to be refuſde:</l>
               <l>Complains of an intended rape,</l>
               <l>Alleadg'd her out-cry, his eſcape;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Joſeph</hi> is in priſon caſt,</l>
               <l>An uncouth fault, for being chaſt.</l>
               <l>But ſtill God bleſt him: to his care,</l>
               <l>The priſoners all committed are.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THe great Creator whoſe all piercing eye</l>
               <l>The ſecretſt corners of our hearts can trie.</l>
               <l>He that their future inclination knows</l>
               <l>Being growne to men, that now art embrioes.</l>
               <l>Elected <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ere good <hi>Abraham</hi> thought</l>
               <l>Old barren <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould a ſonne have brought.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17029:19"/>
               <l>And <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſure, whom God a bleſſing gave</l>
               <l>To weeping <hi>Rachel,</hi> part of it muſt have</l>
               <l>Himſelfe; the Lord nere bleſt a barren wombe,</l>
               <l>And not the iſſue that ſhould from it come.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſephs</hi> belov'd, and bleſt, even from his birth,</l>
               <l>Bleſt in the hollow cavernes of the earth,</l>
               <l>Where being caſt, and then again hal'd thence,</l>
               <l>And by his brethren ſold for twenty pence</l>
               <l>Of ſilver, to thoſe Marchants, who him bare</l>
               <l>To Aegypt, to the houſe of <hi>Putiphar.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There ſold the ſecond time; God in the place</l>
               <l>Of bondage, with his Maſter gives him grace.</l>
               <l>Who, <hi>Joſeph</hi> Steward of his houſe, doth make,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And all he hath, and all for</hi> Joſephs <hi>ſake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is bleſt, and proſpers,</hi> Joſeph <hi>is found just,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As ſeemes by</hi> Putiphar, <hi>his Masters trust:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All's under</hi> Joſephs <hi>hand, nor doth he know</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ought that he hath, but what he eats, or ſo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor doth he looſe by't, <hi>Joſeph</hi> keeps true counts,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Putiphar</hi> to wealth, and honour, mounts</l>
               <l>By his juſt care; but ſee, the devill would ſhow</l>
               <l>A little kindneſſe unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">A deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Joſeph's</hi> a proper man, faire to behold,</l>
               <l>Of goodly ſtature, and a handſome mould,</l>
               <l>His ſparkling eye quicke with attentive care</l>
               <l>Shoots pleaſing beames, yet thoſe, not wanton are;</l>
               <l>His ſmooth white forehead, and unclouded brow</l>
               <l>The open plainneſſe of his heart did ſhow</l>
               <l>Sweet and good natures read, not crafty wiles</l>
               <l>Are hidden, in his undiſſembled ſmiles.</l>
               <l>His long diſhevel'd locks, of curled haire</l>
               <l>From obſcene ſpeeches guard his deafned eare,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17029:19"/>
               <l>His lips faire <hi>Rachels</hi> were, his looks ſo meek,</l>
               <l>His modeſty gave colour to his cheek.</l>
               <l>His head, and heart, were <hi>Jacobs,</hi> juſt, and wiſe,</l>
               <l>All this the fiend pleads, and in's Miſtris eyes,</l>
               <l>Gives him not grace, but liking, not with loves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But with her hot luſts ſtrong temptation proves</l>
               <l>His youth, ſo forcibly as might enrage</l>
               <l>The cold, decayed bloud, of wrincled age.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Joſeph</hi> is unmov'd, a wonder paſt</l>
               <l>Moderne beleefe, hee's tempted, faire, and chaſt.</l>
               <l>Had many women been ſo, t'would from ſpight</l>
               <l>Redeem'd the ſex, and common epithites:</l>
               <l>His no forc'd vertue was, like theirs that be</l>
               <l>Beſt guarded by their owne deformity</l>
               <l>From ſinne, whoſe face is able to deter</l>
               <l>Luſt from themſelves and the adulterer.</l>
               <l>Whoſe looks no more temptation in them have</l>
               <l>Then that they're like the devils, nor to ſave</l>
               <l>Charge or expences was it, nor was he</l>
               <l>To buy his ſinne, or looſe his chaſtity</l>
               <l>At ſo deare rate; his manhood to controule,</l>
               <l>As (ſinners now) with money, and their ſoule.</l>
               <l>Nor lacks he boldneſſe, for his Miſtreſſe ſhe</l>
               <l>Becomes the tempter, and where modeſty</l>
               <l>Moſt hinders luſt, me thinks that grace I finde</l>
               <l>Like Gods reſtringent power, which to mankinde</l>
               <l>The devill doth as 'twere in chains withhold</l>
               <l>From doing of the miſchiefe, that he would;</l>
               <l>Nor wants he youthfull heat, being in the prime</l>
               <l>And flower of his age, the apteſt time</l>
               <l>For ſuch employments, nor wants ought to move</l>
               <l>That might ſeduce him to unlawfull love.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17029:20"/>
               <l>But he that chaſt, and can't be otherwiſe,</l>
               <l>Offers himſelfe a wretched ſacrifice</l>
               <l>To God, when all his bones of ſap are drie,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Cains</hi> lean eares of corne, which in Gods eye</l>
               <l>Was not of all accepted: the moſt high</l>
               <l>Delights not in ſuch barren piety.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note>But <hi>Joſeph</hi> full of vertue, full of truth,</l>
               <l>Remembers his Creator in his youth,</l>
               <l>E're the dayes come which bring him of his grave</l>
               <l>In minde, thoſe dayes, wherein men ſay they have</l>
               <l>No pleaſure: would that grace that ſav'd him then</l>
               <l>From hir inticements, were not loſt 'mongſt men</l>
               <l>Of theſe laſt dayes, ſhe was not foule, nor mean,</l>
               <l>Nor was ſhe old, nor yet a common quean,</l>
               <l>When had ſhe beene all theſe 'ere giv'n a nay,</l>
               <l>How many a youth had caſt his ſoule away</l>
               <l>To ſuch a proffer, they had beene leſſe nice</l>
               <l>Then to deny, more ready to entice.</l>
               <l>She was his Maſters wife, and this offence</l>
               <l>They would have colour'd with obedience</l>
               <l>Still due to her commands: who would have thought,</l>
               <l>I mean what worldly man, but this had brought</l>
               <l>Him to preferment in a way more nigh</l>
               <l>Then his deniall, and fidelity?</l>
               <l>She ſole commandreſſe was in ev'ry thing,</l>
               <l>She could her husband ſway, and he the King,</l>
               <l>But wretched men! and yet Ile nothing ſay,</l>
               <l>Ile not prophane my ſtory, to inveigh</l>
               <l>Or ſcarce to mention them that do not know</l>
               <l>What ſweet content doth with good conſcience flow.</l>
               <l>But from them to the Devill I'le proceed</l>
               <l>Obſerve his plots, ſee with what cunning heed,</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17029:20"/>
               <l>And how induſtrious he his worke doth ply,</l>
               <l>And gives what ſhe could wiſh, conveniency.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When all abroad, none's left but ſhe at home,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Joſeph <hi>bout's buſineſſe in the houſe doth come.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The fiend doth finde his plot may well be croſt,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Joſeph's</hi> baſhfulneſſe would nere accoſt</l>
               <l>His amourous Miſtreſſe, ſhe'l not be withſtood,</l>
               <l>The devill will finde more wayes unto the wood.</l>
               <l>Her plyant boſome with more heat he moves</l>
               <l>At <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſight boldly to breake her loves</l>
               <l>In theſe broad tearms, whom when ſhe firſt doth ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She runs to embrace, and cryes, Come lye with me.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ev'n as a man that in the dead of night</l>
               <l>Some appariſion meets, or ghaſtly ſight,</l>
               <l>He cannot fly, but trembles, and ſtands mute,</l>
               <l>So bluſhing <hi>Joſeph,</hi> at this ſhameleſſe ſuite:</l>
               <l>Whileſt ſhe more bold, commends his matchleſſe ſhape,</l>
               <l>Then on his corrall lips commits a rape.</l>
               <l>And if before her words your wonder breeds,</l>
               <l>She is as plaine, or plainer in her deeds:</l>
               <l>Wealth is her promiſe, and her pledge a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>Alas poore <hi>Joſeph!</hi> what a conflict's this?</l>
               <l>The world, the fleſh, the devill, all at once,</l>
               <l>Thou art beſet, by hels fierce champions.</l>
               <l>They ſtrike his eares with flatt'ries, and they thruſt</l>
               <l>Ev'n at his ſoule with fiery darts of luſt:</l>
               <l>Who arm'd with vertue, in his heart that dwels,</l>
               <l>Makes vaine their malice, and their force repels,</l>
               <l>With flat refuſall, giv'n with due reſpects,</l>
               <l>He reverences his Miſtreſſe, but rejects</l>
               <l>Her impudent entreaties, and with eyes</l>
               <l>Caſt where ſhe may not ſee them, thus replyes:</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17029:21"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Lady) you know that in my hands there are</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More then my Maſter wots, unto my care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All is entrusted that he hath to lye;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There is none greater in the houſe then I:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of all his goods he hath detained none</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From me, except your ſelfe, his wife alone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such was old <hi>Adams</hi> caſe, one fruit forbad,</l>
               <l>Ev n all the world beſides he might have had,</l>
               <l>And that he long'd for, oh unhappy nice</l>
               <l>To ſave his longing, loſt his paradice!</l>
               <l>And ſhall not his example give to me</l>
               <l>Warning enough from the forbidden tree?</l>
               <l>When to my Maſter I was ſold a ſlave,</l>
               <l>His goodneſſe truſted, and ſecurely gave</l>
               <l>His whole ſtate to my keeping: oh 'twere ſhame</l>
               <l>My cos'nage ſhould begin upon his fame!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſides I pray that God my works may bleſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How can I then do this great wickedneſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſinne againſt him? 'twas I hope to try</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your ſervants truth, and his fidelity,</l>
               <l>My honour'd Miſtriſſe, whence theſe words proceed</l>
               <l>Not any meaning to ſo foule a deed:</l>
               <l>Which ſaid, quicke rev'rence made with buſie haſte,</l>
               <l>Not ſtaying for her anſwer forth he paſt:</l>
               <l>And left her more amaz'd, then he at firſt</l>
               <l>When ſhe into her luſtfull paſſions burſt:</l>
               <l>A modeſt bluſh did <hi>Joſephs</hi> cheek beſtaine,</l>
               <l>But in her angry looks all colours raigne;</l>
               <l>All paſſions in her breſt, firſt raging ire</l>
               <l>Inflames her eyes, they ſet the reſt on fire</l>
               <l>Of her ſwolne face, but: oh her loſt delight!</l>
               <l>She fears, and changes, now again ſhee's white.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17029:21"/>
               <l>She grievs, laments, deſpairs; hee'l nere come back</l>
               <l>She cryes, and now ſhee's melancholly black;</l>
               <l>She frets, and frowns, and then as in diſdain</l>
               <l>To be refus'd, ſhe ſcorns, and ſmiles again:</l>
               <l>Now in diſtraction all her paſſions met,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Proteus</hi> himſelf could never counterfet</l>
               <l>So many ſeverall colours, till at laſt</l>
               <l>This mad fit of her contemplation paſt,</l>
               <l>She coms t'her ſelf, and thinks what's done, and ſed,</l>
               <l>And what's the cauſe that ſhe no better ſped:</l>
               <l>Then ſhe conſiders that he was but yong,</l>
               <l>And muſt be ſuppled with a ſmoother tongue:</l>
               <l>She was too rough, thence came her ill ſucceſſe;</l>
               <l>Flattry muſt winne the heart of baſhfulneſſe.</l>
               <l>She ſtudies now encomiums for the rare</l>
               <l>Perfections he's indu'd with, ſuch as were</l>
               <l>Excuſe, ſhe thought, for luſt of worſe degree</l>
               <l>Then hers, for inceſt, or damn'd Sodomie.</l>
               <l>Nature (ſaith ſhe) did nere a body frame</l>
               <l>So excellent; onely to beare a name,</l>
               <l>And to be lookt on, nor will I perſwade</l>
               <l>Thee unto ought, but that for which th'art made,</l>
               <l>Which was not for thy ſelf; thou art not yong,</l>
               <l>Nor deck'd with comelineſſe, nor wiſe, nor ſtrong,</l>
               <l>For thine own onely good, but unto thee</l>
               <l>Nature imparted theſe, that thou mightſt be</l>
               <l>Her ſteward of them; youth and ſtrength are thine,</l>
               <l>(But for her uſe) oh do not thou decline</l>
               <l>From her commands that gave them, ſhe did frame</l>
               <l>All for each others good, and what I claime</l>
               <l>Is by her laws, who never ſure combin'd</l>
               <l>So ſmooth a body, with ſo harſh a minde,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17029:22"/>
               <l>As pretend'ſt to have, all thou canſt ſay</l>
               <l>Is of thy Maſters goodneſſe, canſt thou pay</l>
               <l>His courteſie with greater, all thy life.</l>
               <l>Then this thy kindneſſe to his deareſt wife?</l>
               <l>And i'ſt not meer diſſembling if thou tell</l>
               <l>Thou lov'ſt him, and not her he loves ſo well?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile foure legg'd dwellers in the woods, and hils,</l>
               <l>Both male, and female, whilſt nought curbs their wils</l>
               <l>enjoy their ſweet variety with peace:</l>
               <l>Nature commands them nothing but increaſe.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill do'ſt urge a matrimoniall tye</l>
               <l>Why canſt thou think wiſe ſhe would ere deny</l>
               <l>To man whom ſhe of all things hath poſſeſt</l>
               <l>Thoſe priviledges ſhe hath given a beaſt?</l>
               <l>But more and ſtronger charms ſhe doth invent,</l>
               <l>And ſo the fiend had made her eloquent.</l>
               <l>Her words an aged Hermit from his cell</l>
               <l>Might have intic'd, and made him ſue for hell.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Joſeph's</hi> ſtill unmov'd, he gives no eare</l>
               <l>He's full of buſineſſe, and wants time to heare</l>
               <l>Her flattries (in his carriage thus to her</l>
               <l>Were little hopes of being a Courtier).</l>
               <l>Still ſhe aſſayes him whilſt the dev'll her friend</l>
               <l>Makes daily opportunities attend</l>
               <l>Her newer plots, how can they chuſe but hit</l>
               <l>Between the devils and the womans wit</l>
               <l>So cloſely follow'd? for ſhe day by day</l>
               <l>As <hi>Samſons</hi> wife, or his falſe <hi>Dalila,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Importunate, perſues him with her luſt,</l>
               <l>And day by day hath the ſame anſwer juſt.</l>
               <l>At laſt impatient of her oft denyall,</l>
               <l>She now reſolves upon a finall triall:</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17029:22"/>
               <l>And either in her vile attempts ſhee'l ſpeed</l>
               <l>Or on revenge, if not on luſt ſhee'd feed.</l>
               <l>What foule effects do ſuch ſuits propagate,</l>
               <l>If granted, ſhame; and if not granted, hate.</l>
               <l>Thus arm'd in both hands, brings ſhe ſword, and fire.</l>
               <l>Swords of revenge, and flames of foule deſire.</l>
               <l>Here let him chuſe to which he is inclin'd,</l>
               <l>The fiend and ſhe are of the ſelf-ſame minde.</l>
               <l>If with the ſinne he cannot be content,</l>
               <l>Let him reſolve to beare the puniſhment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The folks i'th field, and</hi> Putiphar <hi>at Court,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Joſeph <hi>comes home: oh how do all conſort</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To her vile purpoſe? whilſt his ſerious thought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mus'd on his buſineſſe, ſhe his garment caught:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Speaks her old language, now ſhe tels him plain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He's fast, and ſhall not part with her again</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till ſhe hath had her will: if he refuſe her,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She'l ſwear that he attempted to abuſe her.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He thus put out on's dumps, this troubled more</l>
               <l>His thoughts, then all he mus'd upon before,</l>
               <l>And as for ſuch encounters ill prepar'd,</l>
               <l>He's mute, and ſtruggles as a bird enſnar'd:</l>
               <l>Such were his looks, as when <hi>Suſanna</hi> ſaw</l>
               <l>The wicked Elders from their covert draw.</l>
               <l>Their caſe not much unlike, the ſame they cry,</l>
               <l>His Miſtriſſe and the Elders, do or dye.</l>
               <l>As a ruft fowl, that gladly leaves her plumes</l>
               <l>In the hawks eager talents, and aſſumes</l>
               <l>New wings of fear, from her late danger paſt</l>
               <l>Vntill her ſafety ſhe hath wonne at laſt.</l>
               <l>The like our troubled <hi>Joſeph</hi> forc't to do,</l>
               <l>Forſakes his garment, and his Miſtriſſe too.</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17029:23"/>
               <l>Who thus forlorn, of all her hopes bereft</l>
               <l>Nothing of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but his rayment left,</l>
               <l>And that ſhe kept, a pledge of hir diſdain,</l>
               <l>Not as a pawn, he would return again.</l>
               <l>His father <hi>Jacob</hi> was not troubled more</l>
               <l>When he his colour'd coat had loſt before.</l>
               <l>Then ſhe's now vext, and fretted, ſhe could tear</l>
               <l>The cloak for anger, yet ſhe will forbear,</l>
               <l>And keep it for revenge, her hopes beguil'd</l>
               <l>Makes her to weep, and anger makes her wilde,</l>
               <l>With looks diſtracted now ſhe doth ariſe,</l>
               <l>And with a loud and troubled voyce ſhe cries</l>
               <l>Unto her people, and whilſt they amaz'd</l>
               <l>Upon her ill preſaging count'nance gaz'd,</l>
               <l>She cries out help, as if ſome foe were by</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Hebrew ſlave hath offer'd villany</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To me his Maſters wife; he that's ſo just,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In whom his Maſter doth repoſe ſuch truſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Twas he came in to mock me, till affright</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By my rais'd voyce, he took himſelf to flight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And left for fear, or ſhame, or both you ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This coat, the witneſſe of his luſt with me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fine Devill ſtill, what plot hath ever been yet</l>
               <l>Croſt with th'old inſtrument the woman wit,</l>
               <l>Whom he thought fitteſt 'mongſt the creatures all</l>
               <l>To compaſſe a damnation generall,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Adam's</hi> ruine; ſhe ſo ſerv'd him then</l>
               <l>That he hath us'd the ſelf ſame hand agen,</l>
               <l>In moſt of's plots e're ſince, upon juſt <hi>Lot</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By wine, and women, he a conqueſt got</l>
               <l>No pow'r but womans ever could ſubvert</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>David,</hi> a man choſe after Gods own heart;</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17029:23"/>
               <l>Then which ſucceſſe he choſe to ſet upon</l>
               <l>The ſtrong, and wiſe, <hi>Samſon,</hi> and <hi>Solomon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So holy <hi>Job</hi> was tempted: women are</l>
               <l>Like Angels, and the good may half compare</l>
               <l>With them for glory, did heav'ns brightneſſe ſhine</l>
               <l>As oft upon them, they were as divine.</l>
               <l>The bad ones are the fleſh that tempt to evill,</l>
               <l>And almoſt do more miſchiefe then the devill.</l>
               <l>Fit inſtruments for him, to death they lead,</l>
               <l>The Wiſeman ſaith, her paths unto the dead.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18.</note>
               </l>
               <l>They're like mans evill genius, and attend</l>
               <l>As his bad angel for ſome wicked end.</l>
               <l>The beſt things when they from their goodneſſe fall,</l>
               <l>And be corrupted, prove the worſt of all.</l>
               <l>'Angels that fell are devils ſince their curſe,</l>
               <l>But beauteous woman falne from vertue, worſe.</l>
               <l>Such was this dame, who ſeeking to betray</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poore</hi> Joſeph <hi>for his innocence doth lay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His cloak ſafe, till his Lords return, to whom</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She thus preſents it at his comming home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such are the ſervants you for me provide,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Hebrew ſlave o'refraught with luſt and pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Came in to mock me, till my ſhreiks for fear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Made him forgo his cloak, and leave it here.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Me thinks with ſuch a brow vext <hi>Samſon</hi> ey'd</l>
               <l>His father that reſtrain'd him from his bride.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Joſephs</hi> angry brethren, did behold him,</l>
               <l>When they againſt him roſe, before they ſold him:</l>
               <l>As now his Maſter doth, who will not ſtay</l>
               <l>To heare him what he for himſelf can ſay.</l>
               <l>Anger contracts his brow, his eyes ſhoot fire,</l>
               <l>His wroth is kindled, will the ſlave aſpire</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17029:24"/>
               <l>To all I have? Is there not in his hands</l>
               <l>Enough already? and with that commands</l>
               <l>Him to perpetuall priſon, too unjuſt</l>
               <l>A guerdon for inviolated truſt.</l>
               <l>Yet in his anger did ſome love appeare,</l>
               <l>'Twas to a place where the Kings priſoners were.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But God thats ev'ry where is there likewiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And gives him favour in his keepers eyes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who a new charge commits unto his care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ev'n all the priſoners that in priſon are.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Joſeph <hi>doth all, the keeper takes his reſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And looks to nothing, but ſtill</hi> Joſeph's <hi>bleſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ſee the Lord his own that nere forſakes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Makes all to thrive that</hi> Joſeph <hi>undertakes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who cheerfull ſtill, and no way diſcontent</l>
               <l>For his loſt liberty, or puniſhment:</l>
               <l>His cleare ſoul knowing, that for no offence</l>
               <l>He ſuffer'd, onely for his innocence.</l>
               <l>And cheerfull well he may be, each place proves</l>
               <l>A heaven unto him, whereſoe're he moves.</l>
               <l>By God's dread preſence, as by Kings reſort,</l>
               <l>Each petty cottage doth become a Court.</l>
               <l>As was the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> bleſt,</l>
               <l>Whilſt in his walls the ſacred Ark did reſt:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Joſeph</hi> now in jayl (no doubt) it were</l>
               <l>A happineſſe to be a priſoner there.</l>
               <l>The keeper finds his bleſſings whilſt he ſees</l>
               <l>With admiration his encreaſe of fees.</l>
               <l>Great priſoners daily flock, like <hi>Labans</hi> ſheep,</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>Jacob</hi> did his paſtures keep.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17029:24"/>
            <head>THE SOOTH-SAYER: OR, The third Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 40.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>The Butler and the Baker, both</l>
               <l>To priſon ſent in <hi>Pharoh's</hi> wroth.</l>
               <l>They ſeverall dreams to <hi>Joſeph</hi> told,</l>
               <l>Who their meanings did unfold.</l>
               <l>The Butler whom his news reſtor'd</l>
               <l>He in his own behalf implor'd:</l>
               <l>But with him thankleſſe, and unkinde,</l>
               <l>Being out of ſight, is out of minde.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd after theſe things, lo, it came to paſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharoh</hi> offended with his Butler was:</l>
               <l>And his chiefe Baker, whom (being wroth) he ſent</l>
               <l>Together both, to cloſe impriſonment:</l>
               <l>Ev'n to the place where <hi>Joſeph</hi> was in ward,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whoſe charge the Captain of the guard</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17029:25"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Committed them, where for a ſeaſon he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did ſerve them both, and bare them company.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There they continued, till ſome days were paſt,</l>
               <l>Impatient with their durance both: at laſt</l>
               <l>With froward vexing they out weare the light,</l>
               <l>And in unquiet ſlumbers ſpend the night,</l>
               <l>Untill as wearied both, a nap they take</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Each with a ſeverall dream i'th'morne doth wake.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When</hi> Joſeph <hi>early comming to ſalute</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His charge, he finds them ſullen both and mute.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sure mans eternall ſoul, hath here ſome ſence</l>
               <l>(As other ſpirits) oth'pleniſcience</l>
               <l>Which unto them hereafter ſhall be given</l>
               <l>(Their fleſhly droſſe being purg'd away) in heav'n.</l>
               <l>And did not our groſſe bodies it deny</l>
               <l>Undoubtedly each man might prophecy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilſt our dull carcaſſes, are charm'd with ſleep,</l>
               <l>Still as in death: our ſoul his watch doth keep:</l>
               <l>No outward objects interpoſe, to hale</l>
               <l>Included fancy forth; the naturall</l>
               <l>Thoughts of our ſouls preſented, then we finde,</l>
               <l>And dream the fears, or wiſhes of our minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The knowing ſoul, then, privy to th'entent</l>
               <l>Of following fate, diſcover would th'event</l>
               <l>To th'corps, and wanting pow'r to do't at full</l>
               <l>Speaks in the language of an oracle.</l>
               <l>With which the body waking from his trance</l>
               <l>Is more afflicted then with ignorance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So 'twas with theſe, who underſtood the news,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.14.</note>Their dreaming fancies brought them; as the Jews</l>
               <l>Chriſts parables: and no more, then th'Eunuch did</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſay</hi>'s miſterious prophecy, as he rid</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17029:25"/>
               <l>Before hee met with <hi>Philip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30.</note> this did vexe</l>
               <l>Their troubled ſences, and ſo much perplexe</l>
               <l>Their mind with doubts; as ſhould a pardon come</l>
               <l>To one condemn'd, he might miſdoubt his doome,</l>
               <l>And ſentence in it, till it were unſeal'd,</l>
               <l>And the glad news, with the contents reveal'd:</l>
               <l>Such were their fears, they always us'd to be</l>
               <l>A little cheer'd with <hi>Joſeph's</hi> company.</l>
               <l>But now when he his morning wiſhes had</l>
               <l>Giv'n, ſtill he finds them diſcontent and ſad.</l>
               <l>Their pale aſpects, which with an o're clowded brow,</l>
               <l>And wrinckled forhead, made them ſeem as though</l>
               <l>Th'unpleaſing fancies not with ſleep forſaking</l>
               <l>Their troubled thoughts, ſtill wrought upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waking.</l>
               <l>Such was wretch't <hi>Hamans</hi> face,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heſt</hi> 6.</note> when he deſcride</l>
               <l>The ſtrange cataſtrophe of all his pride</l>
               <l>So look't <hi>Caldeas</hi> King,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.</note> when midſt of all</l>
               <l>His jollity, he ſpide upon the wall</l>
               <l>The characters unknown, the dreadfull hand</l>
               <l>Which all the ſages could not underſtand.</l>
               <l>So penſive were theſe priſoners till ſome pauſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paſt,</hi> Joſeph <hi>ſilence breaks and asks the cauſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What mean theſe heavy looks? they both reply</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yong man, tis more then our loſt liberty</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That now afflicts us, we have each this night,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dreampt ſeverall dreams, and here is none that might</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſcoſe the hidden meaning, or make knowne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To us the right interpretation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Perchance they may devine ſome good event,</l>
               <l>Some eaſe, or end, of our impriſonment.</l>
               <l>Be not diſmaid, replide the holy youth,</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17029:26"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come not ſuch ſecrets from the God of truth?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cheer up your down-caſt hearts, and you ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God makes his ſervants wiſe: pray tell them me</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To whom the Butler as a good portent</l>
               <l>Of's lucky fancy and the good it meant,</l>
               <l>Firſt clears his clouded face, and taking heart,</l>
               <l>He thus to <hi>Joſeph</hi> doth his dream impart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Butlers dreame,</note>
                  <hi>Me thought my fancy gave unto my ſight</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A fruitfull vine which ſpread it ſelf forth right</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into three branches, on whoſe boughs appeare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The three most pleaſant ſeaſons of the yeare:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It ſprings, and buds, and then it bloſſoms bore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At laſt with ripn'd grapes all cluſtred ore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I gather'd ſome, which as I then did think</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I cruſh't in</hi> Pharaohs <hi>cup, and gave him drink.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom good <hi>Joſeph</hi> being loath to hide</l>
               <l>Such welcome news from him, thus replide.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
                  <hi>The fruitfull branches that were ſpread three ways,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By their interpretation are three days:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let not thoſe houres ſeem tedious, which being ſpent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are the laſt days of thy impriſonment.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The King ſhall lift thine head, and ſhall reſtore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thee then to fill his cup as heretofore.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But when as I foretell you finde it ſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Remember</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and ſome kindneſſe ſhow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mention my name to</hi> Pharoh, <hi>free me hence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And my good tydings have full recompence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I from the</hi> Hebrew <hi>land was ſtoln a childe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor hath my youth committed ought ſo vilde</l>
               <l>As to deſerve the rigor that thus ſtays</l>
               <l>Me here to languiſh out my beſt of days,</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17029:26"/>
               <l>In obſcure lazineſſe; with ſo ſmall ſcope,</l>
               <l>Able to breake the very heart of hope.</l>
               <l>All that my worſt accuſer e're could lay</l>
               <l>Vnto my charge, I once did diſobey</l>
               <l>My Maſters wife, in a command that went</l>
               <l>Againſt my conſcience; and was therefore ſent</l>
               <l>Here where you ſee me; 'twas no other fault</l>
               <l>That damn'd me to this melancholy vault,</l>
               <l>Where were that axiom true, that ſome doe hold,</l>
               <l>Griefe makes men gray, I had ere this grown old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now as you finde my truth, remember me</l>
               <l>By the prediction of your liberty.</l>
               <l>Your dreame expounded, I have clear'd your doubt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>But dreame not when I ſhall my ſelfe come out:</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe your kinde remembrance quit me well,</l>
               <l>By giving me what I to you foretell.</l>
               <l>The Butler like a Courtier promis'd where</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Ioſeph</hi> makes his period with a teare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this the Baker having underſtood,</l>
               <l>To'thers interpretation was good,</l>
               <l>Rous'd up himſelfe, and herewith comforted.<note place="margin">The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers dreame interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus told his dreame, behold upon my head</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Were three white baskets, th'uppermoſt me thought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With all choyce kindes of</hi> Pharoh's <hi>bake-meats fraught,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where loe the birds, that round about me fled,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did cat them out o'th basket on my head.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To whom, thus</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>(loathing with delays,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Worſe to torment him) telleth that three dayes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His three white baskets are, whoſe ſhort time ſpent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt be free from thy impriſonment;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then an end of all thy cares ſhalt make,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſhall the King thine head from off thee take;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17029:27"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>And cauſe thee to be hang'd upon a tree,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And birds ſhall eat thy fleſh from off of thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ends, whil'ſt they with hope and feare,</l>
               <l>True picture of thoſe different paſſions were.</l>
               <l>Nor will I otherwiſe deſcribe their ſtation,</l>
               <l>But each was like his dreames interpretation:</l>
               <l>Th'one full of hope, the other of deſpaire;</l>
               <l>But all proves true, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did declare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For the third following morne it came to paſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That</hi> Pharoh's <hi>birth day then ſolemniz'd was:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mirth and the voyce of joy the heavens invade,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt he feaſt for all his ſervants made.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To which the priſoners call'd, he lifts their head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The one's reſtor'd, the t'other puniſhed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With ſhame, and verifying</hi> Ioſephs <hi>words,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hang'd, and his fleſh devoured by the birds.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Meane while, th' advanced Butler, too ingrate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Forgets poore</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>and his wretched ſtate.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Courtiers have buſie heads, the breath of Kings</l>
               <l>Takes from them cleane the ſenſe of meaner things</l>
               <l>Th'have other thoughts to thinke on, then to know</l>
               <l>Friends low in ſtate, when their high fortunes flow.</l>
               <l>Th'have all faire language, and that's freely ſpent;</l>
               <l>Their promiſe too is but a complement.</l>
               <l>No ſtrangers buſineſſe in their heads can ſtand,</l>
               <l>Without ſome memorandums in their hand.</l>
               <l>But pardon me, you noble ſoules, that be</l>
               <l>Attendants fit for ſacred Majeſty.</l>
               <l>Men farre above my Muſe, weake to ſet forth</l>
               <l>Your praiſe: leſſe able to impayr your worth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know the Court's the onely Shoole to teach</l>
               <l>Humanity, and to attain the reach</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17029:27"/>
               <l>Of wit: it is, what need more words be ſpent?</l>
               <l>Under the Kings immediate government:</l>
               <l>Where brave mindes, that from glories of the place,</l>
               <l>Vertue and worth derive, their Princes grace</l>
               <l>Abuſing not, but ſtudying to confer't</l>
               <l>To his increaſe of love, upon deſert:</l>
               <l>Have all thoſe Angels plac'd by heav'n t'attend</l>
               <l>The King, (his ſtate and perſon to defend)</l>
               <l>So many better geniuſſes to tell,</l>
               <l>And prompt them, both to live, and counſell well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to conceive there be 'bout honours ſeat,</l>
               <l>Courtiers like this i'th ſtory, it would whet</l>
               <l>The dulleſt Muſe, and make milde patience ſtrain</l>
               <l>For Satyres, being inſpired by diſdain</l>
               <l>Of ſuch a thankleſſe wretch, that hath forgot</l>
               <l>His comforter in priſon, minding not</l>
               <l>Who rais'd his drooping head, and hopes deſcry'de</l>
               <l>To him, that elſe might there for griefe have dyde.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17029:28"/>
            <head>THE COVRTIER: OR, The fourth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 41.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharoh</hi> dreamt, the Sages ſent</l>
               <l>For, cannot tell him what it meant.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> called for, declares</l>
               <l>Th' approaching Famine, and prepares</l>
               <l>Againſt it. <hi>Pharoh</hi> doth him grace,</l>
               <l>And yeelds in Court a ſecond place</l>
               <l>To him; his bleſsing's well begun,</l>
               <l>The King a wife, God gives him Sonnes.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>POore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtill a priſoner, looks to heare</l>
               <l>From his inlarged friend, with patient eare</l>
               <l>For two years ſpace: and freedome he expects</l>
               <l>From him, whoſe life and practice are neglects.</l>
               <l>But now he findes his error, knowes it can</l>
               <l>Nothing availe him to confide in man.</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17029:28"/>
               <l>Man nere ſo mindfull, 's but a means to do</l>
               <l>What God thinks fit, and gives his bleſſing to.</l>
               <l>This the <hi>Bethulians</hi> knew, whoſe ſtate more bad</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> and an Advocate they had</l>
               <l>Carefull as being a party in the caſe,</l>
               <l>Hopefull as beauty, or her pleading face.<note place="margin">Iudeth.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Yet they no confidence, repoſe ſhe,</l>
               <l>They hope a happy means from God may be</l>
               <l>For their deliverance: from hence they take</l>
               <l>Some courage and their joint petitions make</l>
               <l>That God would bleſſe her with ſucceſſe as faire,</l>
               <l>As was the undertaker. <hi>Samſons</hi> haire</l>
               <l>Gave but ſmall hope to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of defence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16</note>
               </l>
               <l>When as the Spirit was departed thence.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 38.21. <hi>King.</hi> 20 7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What power is in dride figs to heale the fore</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iudah's</hi> King: are <hi>Iſraels</hi> waters more</l>
               <l>Healthfull then thoſe of <hi>Syria,</hi> that they can,</l>
               <l>By waſhing clean the Leper <hi>Naaman?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What vertue hath unleſſe God bleſſing meet</l>
               <l>The Prophes ſalt, to make the waters ſweet?</l>
               <l>The greateſt means in miſery to redreſſe it</l>
               <l>As fruitleſſe is, except our God do bleſſe it.</l>
               <l>Men have not powre to think of what they ſee</l>
               <l>Unleſſe the Lord inſtruct their memory.</l>
               <l>As now in his good time he brought to paſſe,</l>
               <l>The Butler mindfull of poor <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was.</l>
               <l>Though late, when <hi>Pharoh,</hi> (for crowns cannot keep</l>
               <l>Care from Kings heads) was troubled in his ſleep.</l>
               <l>Fancies diſturb'd work on his reſtleſſe brain</l>
               <l>He dreamp't, and wak't, &amp; ſlept, and dreampt again,</l>
               <l>Again affrighted wakes: and ſends to call</l>
               <l>His Sages, and Magicians, and for all</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17029:29"/>
               <l>That uſed to deſcant on ſuch miſtique theams</l>
               <l>But none can tell the meaning of his dreams.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long had they mus'd, and heer one walk't alone</l>
               <l>Biting his nailes in contemplation.</l>
               <l>There t'other ſcratch't his head as if he were</l>
               <l>Aſſur'd without all doubt to find it there.</l>
               <l>One waves his hand, another ſtroaks his beard,</l>
               <l>A third ſit ſtill, and with his face uprear'd,</l>
               <l>Looks whence it came; and ſure hee'l fetch it far</l>
               <l>That to a ſtrict account calls ſtar by ſtar,</l>
               <l>The hoſt of Heaven, inquiring the effects</l>
               <l>Of the cloſe viſion from their aſpects</l>
               <l>But hearſalike, that queſtions powr's ſo high</l>
               <l>The muſique of the ſphears, and their reply.</l>
               <l>Heer one more ſerious plodding then the reſt</l>
               <l>Falls faſt aſleep, whether his minde oppreſt,</l>
               <l>With too much ſtudy were, or his intent</l>
               <l>By his own dream to what <hi>Pharoh's</hi> meant,</l>
               <l>He like the reſt ſucceeds: their heads they joyn'd,</l>
               <l>But ſtill ſo many a head, ſo many a mind.</l>
               <l>Now like the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> that undertook</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Samſons</hi> dark riddle, ſo the Sages look.</l>
               <l>They greatly troubled are, but <hi>Pharoh</hi> more,</l>
               <l>His looks are like his Butlers heretofore,</l>
               <l>Who happily was thus by <hi>Pharoh's</hi> face</l>
               <l>Made mindfull of his own and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> caſe:</l>
               <l>And whether's pity, or promiſe were the thing</l>
               <l>That moved him if to pleaſe, or eaſe the King,</l>
               <l>It were I know not: but he thus began</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With reverence made, This day, ô King, I can</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Remember well my faults,</hi> Pharoh <hi>was wroth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With his two ſervants, and moſt juſtly both</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17029:29"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ſelf, and his chief Baker put inward</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into the Captain's priſon of the Guard.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where being at once orecome with grief extream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And troubled thoughts, each of us dreampt a dream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'th' ſelf-ſame night our ſleeps imaginations</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>According juſt to their interpretations.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We wak'd and ſadly mus'd, till a young man</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Putiphars <hi>ſervant, priſoner with us than</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An</hi> Hebrew <hi>captive, unto whom we told</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our dreams, their hidden meanings did unfold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And as unto us both he did foretell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>According to our dreams it ſo befell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me he reſtor'd unto my former place,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But him he hang'd, and ſo it came to paſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He had not fully ended, when as one</l>
               <l>Quick in obedience covets to be gone</l>
               <l>Ere he knowes half his errand, <hi>Pharoh</hi> ſo</l>
               <l>Would ere whether or for whom he know,</l>
               <l>But now the tale is ended, when in haſt,</l>
               <l>He calls a meſſenger that comes as faſt.</l>
               <l>He ſends him to the priſon out of hand</l>
               <l>And thinks the time long whilſt he gave command.</l>
               <l>The poſt upon the wings of ſpeed doth fly,</l>
               <l>And come, calls out for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> haſtily.</l>
               <l>Now the delay is his, here lyes the ſport,</l>
               <l>Hee'l ſhave and ſhift himſelf ere come to Court</l>
               <l>And all into a comely order bring,</l>
               <l>May make him fit to ſtand before the King:</l>
               <l>'Twas a good <hi>omen</hi> ſure, a lucky ſigne</l>
               <l>Which did his future Courtierſhip divine:</l>
               <l>That he ſo much of ſpruceneſſe then bethought him</l>
               <l>When news of freedom from the King was brought him.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17029:30"/>
               <l>Who the mean while impatient of delay,</l>
               <l>Begins to wonder at the pris'ners ſtay;</l>
               <l>But now's appeas'd <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by this is there</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pharoh</hi> bent to ſpeak as he to heare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I dreampt a dream, and here is none that can</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Interpret it, but I have heard, young man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of thee as one that is well ſeen and wiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In knowledge of ſuch hidden myſteries.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom with a ſubmiſſive bending knee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> replyes, 'tis not ô King in me:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But God ſhall give to thy joyes increaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By his poor ſervant a reply of peace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pleas'd with his gracefull modeſty the King</l>
               <l>Reviews his ingenious face as promiſing,</l>
               <l>As to our Harveſt hopes when one eſpies</l>
               <l>The ſetting Sun with redneſſe leave the Skies.</l>
               <l>And with this anſwer cheer'd he now thinks long</l>
               <l>To hear more comfort from ſo ſweet a tongue,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Pharohs <hi>dream.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>And therefore thus: When as me thought I ſtood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vpon the rivers bank behold ſev'n good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fat, and wel-favor'd kine, from thence did riſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And graz'd i'th medow, but whilſt my pleas'd eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Viewd their broad back that did with ſmoothneſſe ſhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The troubled waters ſent ſeven other kine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So poor, lean fleſhed, as I never ey'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Meer bare anatomies cover'd with a hide,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's none in</hi> Egypt <hi>ſuch, I took them ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As foyles the others goodneſſe to preſent</l>
               <l>By their deformities, for neer till now</l>
               <l>Did I obſerve ſuch beauty in a Cow</l>
               <l>As in the other ſeven, on whom they ſet</l>
               <l>And cleand devour'd, but nere the fatter yet.</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17029:30"/>
               <l>Me-thought in killing them the ugly beaſts</l>
               <l>Look't like ſo many death in their arreſts,</l>
               <l>But in devouring they reſemblance have</l>
               <l>To the inſatiate and unfruitfull grave.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which having ſeen, my labouring fancy broak,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sleep left my wearied eyes, and I awoak,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But whilſt my thoughts were fixt upon this theam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ſlept again, and dreampt another dream.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>And then behold there came into my view</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A ſprouting ſtalk, wherin ſev'n ears there grew</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good, rank, and full of corn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pharohs</hi> ſecond dreame.</note> 
                  <hi>but whilſt I hung</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My eyes on that fair object, lo there ſprung</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cloſe to thoſe ears ſev'n others, thinne, and pin'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wither'd, and blaſted by the Eaſtern wind.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And theſe devour'd, the ſwoln fruit burdned ears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt yet no change at all in them appears:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All this have I to the Magicians told,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But none the hidden meaning can unfold.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>God hath to</hi> Pharoh <hi>his entents made known</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then anſwer'd</hi> Ioſeph, Pharoh's <hi>dream is one.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For by the ſeven good kine, ſev'n yeers are ſhewn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So by the ſev'n good ears, the dream is one.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And the ſev'n leaner kine, and empty ears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That came up after, are ſev'n other yeers.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The firſt being good, and full, betoken plenty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But famine's threatned in the leane, and empty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The thing that I have ſpoken to the King</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not I, but God hath ſpoken, and ſhall bring</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shortly to paſſe, ſev'n yeares of plenty ſhall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crowne all your harveſt hopes ev'n throughout all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fruitfull Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>after then</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In vain the labour of the husband-men</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17029:31"/>
               <l>Shall till the earth, whereon no corn ſhall ſtand,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plenty ſhall be forgotten in the land.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From which, as from plow'd ſands, expect no crop,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ſeven yeers famine ſhall conſume it up,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for it doubled twice to</hi> Pharoh <hi>was,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis ſtabliſht, and ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God hath eſtabliſht it, let</hi> Pharoh <hi>than</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Throughout his territories find a man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wiſe, and diſcreet, and let it be his care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſee that officers appointed are</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To take the fift part up, throughout the land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And lay the corn all under</hi> Pharohs <hi>hand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let the Cities be well ſtor'd with food,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By the neighbouring countrey whilſt the yeers are good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since God the bad enſuing hath declar'd</l>
               <l>Let not the famine find us unprepar'd.</l>
               <l>But ſo let <hi>Pharoh</hi> gainſt thoſe barren yeers</l>
               <l>Provide, that not a ſoul may periſh heer,</l>
               <l>For want: let forrain Lands the better fare</l>
               <l>By us, and owe their ſafeties to our care.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heer</hi> Ioſeph <hi>ends, and lo the thing ſeem'd good</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Pharoh's <hi>eyes, and in their eyes that ſtood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>About him, to whom thus the King began.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is there in all the Land a fitter man?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To whom Gods Spirit ſhews ſuch hidden things,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He keeps Gods ſecrets, and is fit for Kings.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then turning him about to</hi> Ioſeph <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Since of thee God hath 'bove all others made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His choice, theſe holy counſels to diſcloſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That proves thee fitteſt, I have therefore choſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thee as the only man, diſcreet, and wiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To do according to thine own advice.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17029:31"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt be o're my houſe, what thou thinkſt fit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall be my peoples law, who unto it</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall yeeld obedience, great as is mine own</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall thy command in</hi> Egypt <hi>be, i'th' throne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ile only be above, the voyce is thine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of power, the eyes of Majeſty be mine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now have I ſet thee over all my Land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Witneſſe this Ring, which taking from his hand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He put on</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>finger, and array'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him in rich veſtures of fine linnen made,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such as the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Princes wore of old,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And on his neck he put a chain of gold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then in his ſecond chariot made him ride</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt bow the knee before him, people cry'de:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Ruler he, ore all the Land doth make him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which to confirme he turn'd, and thus beſpak him.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis I am</hi> Pharoh; <hi>nor without thee ſhall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A man lift up his hand or foot through all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Realme of</hi> Egypt, <hi>then to crown his life</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With true content, he fits him with a wife,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fair</hi> Aſenath, <hi>a goodly prize alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She was</hi> Potipherahs <hi>daughter, Prieſt of</hi> Un.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> rais'd unto the height of powre,</l>
               <l>In ſhorter ſpace, then the quick ſpringing flowre:</l>
               <l>That asks but one nights growth, he that of late</l>
               <l>Wayl'd in a dungeon, fils a chair of State,</l>
               <l>Oh what a bounteous King found he to do it!</l>
               <l>Nay, what a bounteous God that mov'd him to it!</l>
               <l>Then think on <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> caſe what ere thou be,</l>
               <l>Diſpair not, art in priſon? ſo was he,</l>
               <l>Perhaps, thou'lt ſay, thou haſt no skill in dreams,</l>
               <l>No revelations, God hath other means.</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17029:32"/>
               <l>Doubt not his power, nor providence, he can</l>
               <l>That hath created all, ſure helpe a man</l>
               <l>More wayes than one: doſt thou complaine th'art poore,</l>
               <l>And ſuffer'ſt want? <hi>Iob</hi> ſurely ſuffred more.</l>
               <l>Doe croſſes vexe thee? or afflictions rod</l>
               <l>Torment thy ſoule? have patience ſtill in God:</l>
               <l>Wayt on, pray to, truſt in him, onely he</l>
               <l>Can cure, and cleanſe, and eaſe thy malady.</l>
               <l>Do'ſt ſtrive with ſtrong temptations, to him then</l>
               <l>God caſt ſeven divels out of <hi>Magdalen?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Art ſicke, or ſinfull? pray'r a cure did winne</l>
               <l>For <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> ſore, and <hi>Davids</hi> ſinne.</l>
               <l>Perchance th'aſt truſted, praid, and waited long;</l>
               <l>Looke backe to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he was ſure but young</l>
               <l>When firſt he taſted ſorrow, vext between</l>
               <l>Bondage, Luſt, Priſons, and his Brethrens ſpleen:</l>
               <l>Ev'n from his very cradle, yet he ſtayd,</l>
               <l>He waited long with patience, long he prayd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ere comfort came; for loe when he appears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before the King, his age was thirty yeers;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Out of whoſe preſence, to his charge he went,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And overſeers throughout</hi> Aegypt <hi>ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the ſeven plenteous, whilſt all their grounds</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brought forth by handfuls, ev'ry place abounds</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With goodly crops, the ſight whereof began</l>
               <l>To cheer the Clowne, and glad the Husbandman.</l>
               <l>They ply their truſt, their labours never ceaſe</l>
               <l>To treaſure up the fruitfull earths increaſe.</l>
               <l>Me thinks I ſee them, like the buſie ſwarme,</l>
               <l>When their commander hums, and gives th'alarme:</l>
               <l>They iſſue forth, and their diſperſed powre</l>
               <l>Coaſts every field, and light on ev'ry flowre,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17029:32"/>
               <l>To make their ſweet extractions, and they ſtrive</l>
               <l>Who ſhall unlade him oftneſt at the hive:</l>
               <l>They fill their bags, and gladly homewards flye</l>
               <l>With pleaſant burdens in their painfull thigh:</l>
               <l>Onely this diffrence makes 'twixt them and theſe,</l>
               <l>The gatherers went not murmuring as the Bees.</l>
               <l>But with their ſilent paces all along</l>
               <l>They trudge like Ants, a people wiſe, not ſtrong,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.25.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Preventing want in plenty, with their paine,</l>
               <l>So each of theſe came laden home with graine.</l>
               <l>They glean'd apace, whilſt corn like ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds they found,</l>
               <l>And ſtor'd the Cities fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the neighbouring ground:</l>
               <l>Th'y have gathred much, the Granaries are fild</l>
               <l>With all th'abundance which the land doth yeeld.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi> is now provided 'gainſt her fears,</l>
               <l>Should all the world beſiege her for ſeven years;</l>
               <l>Were they wal'd ſtrong enough, it were no doubt</l>
               <l>But they'd by that, ſtarve the beſiegers out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>His worke now ending,</hi> Ioſeph <hi>takes his reſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with two ſonnes, is ere the famine bleſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Two goodly ſonnes, which</hi> Aſenath <hi>the fayre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vn's <hi>Prieſt and Princes daughter to him bare:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The firſt he call'd</hi> Manaſſeh, <hi>for he ſaid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God of my toyle hath me forgetfull made,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paſt in my Fathers houſe: the ſecond he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nam'd</hi> Ephraim, <hi>for God hath cauſed me</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here to be fruitfull, whither I was ſent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As the place for my affliction meant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But now the time is come that muſt attone</l>
               <l>The dreams with their interpretation:</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Pharoh</hi> findes that <hi>Ioſephs</hi> words are true,</l>
               <l>The good years gone and paſt, and bad enſue:</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:17029:33"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> expects, and now the time appears</l>
               <l>The full are ſwallowed by the blaſted ears.</l>
               <l>Pin'd, famine from all lands comes flocking thither,</l>
               <l>And from all countries men come flocking with her.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> alone hath bread, yet ſome of thoſe</l>
               <l>That were ill husbands, or that did repoſe</l>
               <l>No truſt in <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> words, by this halfe dead</l>
               <l>For their late unbelief, cry out for bread.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But ſtill to</hi> Pharoh <hi>when the people cry'de,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They were to</hi> Ioſeph <hi>ſent to be ſupply'de.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What he ſhall bid you do, to him they went,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who ſold them corn, when all their ſtore was ſpent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The granaries he ſet ope, for there was dearth</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And famine ore the face of all the earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay, now in</hi> Egypts <hi>ſelfe it waxed ſore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till he ſupply'd their daily wants with more,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It rag'd in all lands and all Countries came</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thither for corn, and ask for</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>name.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17029:33"/>
            <head>THE STEVVARD: OR, The fifth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 42.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>To <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from all Countries come</l>
               <l>Th'inhabitants for food mongst whom</l>
               <l>His brethren came plagued with the dearth,</l>
               <l>To him as Steward of the earth,</l>
               <l>For by him are all Nations fed</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> alone abounds in bread.</l>
               <l>Blest with his care, which none denies,</l>
               <l>Save them, he challenged for ſpies.</l>
               <l>To prove their truſt, they muſt agen</l>
               <l>Returning bring young <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Simeon</hi> mean-while in hold remains,</l>
               <l>And they releas'd go home with grain.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>LIke that myſterious Book the Angell gave</l>
               <l>To <hi>Iohn,</hi> are worldlings fond delights, they have</l>
               <l>A ſmack of pleaſure which affects the ſence</l>
               <l>At firſt, but ends in bitter penitence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17029:34"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5.</note>The whore hath honied lips, her perfum'd breath</l>
               <l>Utters words ſmooth as oyle, but unto death</l>
               <l>Her feet make haſte, her ſteps to hell doe tend,</l>
               <l>Sharpneſſe and bitterneſſe are in her end.</l>
               <l>Such in all earthly pleaſures, they whoſe mindes</l>
               <l>Swell with vaine-glory, or whom Mammon blinds,</l>
               <l>The god of this world, that they thinke to be,</l>
               <l>In riches onely true felicity;</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.</note>Like the forgotten dreame of <hi>Babels</hi> King,</l>
               <l>(Which did confuſion to the Sages bring)</l>
               <l>A head of gold, a breaſt of ſilver, they,</l>
               <l>With thighs of braſſe may have, but feet of clay.</l>
               <l>Their glory, riches, joyes, wherein they truſt,</l>
               <l>Being paſt away, their end ſhall be in duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The world like a fond Mother is, and ſmiles</l>
               <l>Upon her own, whom ſhe a time beguiles</l>
               <l>With pleaſures, fading like her ſelfe, (for ſhe</l>
               <l>That hath not, cannot give eternity</l>
               <l>To them) whoſe firſt, and better dayes being paſt,</l>
               <l>Muſt grieve the reſt, and thinke upon their laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>GOD like a gratious Father, but auſtere;</l>
               <l>Firſt, by corrections teacheth his to feare,</l>
               <l>And to be humble, which being taught them, he</l>
               <l>I'th end rewardeth their humility</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 1.</note>With choycer bleſſings, <hi>Iob</hi> he firſt did try,</l>
               <l>By taking of his wealth, his miſery</l>
               <l>Increas'd by ſore diſeaſes, ſoule, and ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Vext to the utmoſt of his patience.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abram</hi> from God receives a ſtrict command</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.2.</note>To ſacrifice his Sonne; with his own hand</l>
               <l>To kill his Childe, having as yet but one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> an heyr to his affliction,</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17029:34"/>
               <l>Hath loſt his beſt lov'd boy: Gods bleſſings here</l>
               <l>T' his children, diffrent from the worlds appear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Whilſt heers a little time, the world doth bleſſe,</l>
               <l>Their end is crownd with endleſſe happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor doth the God of earth and heaven give</l>
               <l>Us onely future hopes, but whilſt we live,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 42.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Feeds us with daily bleſſings: <hi>Iob</hi> increas't</l>
               <l>In wealth; againe, is richeſt of the Eaſt.</l>
               <l>Nor doth good <hi>Abram</hi> like contentment lacke,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſack</hi> is with a bleſſing giv'n him backe:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhall, the dayes are now begun,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.20.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Finde to the ſafeguard of his life, his Sonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The generall dearth that through all nations ran,</l>
               <l>Hath ſhown his lean aſpect in <hi>Canaan;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And pinch'd the holy Patriarks: ten are ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Ioſephs <hi>brethren, all their ſtore being ſpent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For new ſupplyes of corne; for it was ſed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That onely</hi> Aegypt <hi>did abound in bread.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Forwards they ſet, now the firſt motion ſtirres,</l>
               <l>And they prove <hi>Ioſephs</hi> beſt Interpreters.</l>
               <l>The time is come, the ſheaves begin to bend,</l>
               <l>Ten of the ſtarres already doe deſcend,</l>
               <l>The reſt muſt follow: <hi>Iacob</hi> now ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>His rays'd Sonne, and his ſleeping prophecy:</l>
               <l>And he to whom ſo many dreames were known,</l>
               <l>God now declares, and brings to paſſe his own.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For loe his brethren that were come before him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bowing their faces to the earth, adore him.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He's put in minde of's viſion, at firſt view,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though none of them knew him, yet them he knew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And this gives me more wonder then their change,</l>
               <l>His ſtrange remembrance, their oblivion ſtrange.</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:17029:35"/>
               <l>It is not commonly the poore forgot,</l>
               <l>To claime alliance from their friends grown great.</l>
               <l>Nor is't the uſuall way o'th world, that men</l>
               <l>Of riſing fortune ſhould remember then</l>
               <l>Their meane, though neereſt kinne, &amp; much the leſſe</l>
               <l>To be expected, comming in diſtreſſe.</l>
               <l>Looke on their natures, and there ſure ſhould be</l>
               <l>Between them ſome prompting antipathy</l>
               <l>Should make them know, however high eſtated,</l>
               <l>So great an eye-ſore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whom they hated.</l>
               <l>Who on the other ſide, as ſoone as ſpide them,</l>
               <l>(Nor was his memory malice) he deſcride them.</l>
               <l>He found them as he left them, but their eyes</l>
               <l>Were doubtleſſe dazl'd with his dignities:</l>
               <l>Whilſt no revenge, (therefore let none miſtake him)</l>
               <l>Did ſo quick ſighted, but his meekneſſe make him:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He meant no harme unto them, though he ſpoke</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In a ſharpe key, and with a rougher looke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Askes whence they came, when humbly one replyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From</hi> Canaan, <hi>to buy corne; he cals them ſpyes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Canaan <hi>upon a fruitfull ſoyle doth ſtand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flowing with milke and honey: Yee our land</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are come to pry into, to what diſtreſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Famine hath brought it, and what nakedneſſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When trembling, with one ſudden voyce they cry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy ſervants true men are, and come to buy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Food for our aged Father, we were borne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All one mans ſonnes, and hither come for corne;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our alter'd ſoyle doth not afford us graine;</l>
               <l>Twice hath the reaper lookt for worke in vaine.</l>
               <l>Twich have the Plowmans toyle and ſeed inhum'd</l>
               <l>Untimely froſts, unkindely heats conſum'd.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17029:35"/>
               <l>Our ſtore is ſpent, nor have we hope to live,</l>
               <l>Unleſſe your goodneſſe do our wants relieve.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Still <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who but what he knew did heare,</l>
               <l>Chang'd not his noat, but bids obſerve their feare,</l>
               <l>Their tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling joynts, faint voyce, &amp; down-caſt eys,</l>
               <l>True ſignes of guilt, diſcovered them for ſpyes.</l>
               <l>They know not how to look, nor what to ſay?</l>
               <l>Their poſtures, ev'ry thing ſeem'd to betray</l>
               <l>Them to his jealous fury: if they muſe</l>
               <l>Or whiſper, then they'r forging an excuſe;</l>
               <l>If they be ſilent, that their guilt implyes;</l>
               <l>Their boldneſſe impudence, their language lyes.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill conſidering that no ſuch they were</l>
               <l>As he ſuſpected them, they perſevere</l>
               <l>More confident as in their tale begun.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They were twelve brethren, and the yongeſt ſonne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their aged Fathers fondneſſe did detaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At home with him: the twelfth alas was ſlaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By what miſchance unknowne: they ſtoutly ſtand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vpon't, they came not to deſcry the land.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their honeſt errand ſerv'd not to diſguiſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So bad intents: but ſtill I call'd you ſpyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anſwer'd the ſubtile</hi> Ioſeph; <hi>thus you ſhall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prove my ſurmiſes vain: chooſe one of all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That may goe up with a ſupply of graine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The reſt with me in priſon ſhall remaine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yee ſhall not hence by</hi> Pharohs <hi>life I ſweare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vntill I ſee your yongeſt brother here.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This is the way to prove my doubts untrue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And whether there be any truſt in you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let one then fetch him, here your ſafety lyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For by the life of</hi> Pharoh, <hi>elſe y'are ſpyes.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17029:36"/>
               <l>At this with feare and trouble ſore diſmaid,</l>
               <l>Not knowing what to ſay, they nothing ſaid.</l>
               <l>But as they muſing on each other ſtar'd,</l>
               <l>Ioſeph <hi>for three dayes put them all in ward:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then calling them before him, they appeare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He bids doe this and live, for loe I feare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God; and if as ye ſay, ye true men be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let of your brethren, one ſtay here with me;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The reſt goe home in peace, with good ſupply,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſtave off famine from your family:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But ſee your yongeſt brothers preſence prove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your truth returning, ſo no hand ſhall move</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Againſt your lives, or ſafeties, or withſtand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your peacefull traffique with us in the land</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, when ſeeing no way to prevent,</l>
               <l>Of ſad neceſſity they were content.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet with their captive brother, ere they goe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They take a little time to vent their woe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guilt ſurely hangs upon us, and our God</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſaw our ſinne, now threatneth with the rod</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of vengeance, timely had our griefe bin ſpent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ere we our harmeleſſe brother, hither ſent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We turn'd him pittileſſe, and deafned eares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When he in anguiſh of his ſoule, and teares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gently beſought us, but alas, too late,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We nere repent us of our curſed hate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whence all theſe miſchiefes their beginnings take:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We juſtly puniſh't are for</hi> Ioſephs <hi>ſake.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> Aegypt, <hi>ev'n the place where we him ſent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God hath ordained for our puniſhment.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas cryes</hi> Ruben, <hi>had you bin ſo wiſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As t' have given any eare to my advice,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:17029:36"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>This had not bin, when I with language milde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſſwaded you from ſinning 'gainſt the childe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But following then your raſh and furious mood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold th'event, God hath requir'd his blood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Little thought they that</hi> Ioſeph <hi>was ſo neare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The other party to theſe preſents there.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For he dealt ſubtly with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That makes himſelfe the ſlye companion</l>
               <l>Of theeves, or traytors, or perchance would be</l>
               <l>More ſatisfide in ſome home jealouſie.</l>
               <l>He fains long deafneſſe, or it may be, can</l>
               <l>Tranſlate his tone, like ſome outlandiſh man.</l>
               <l>Meane while ſecurely they their miſchiefes vent,</l>
               <l>And hee's made privy to their cloſe intent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As farre deceiv'd here,</hi> Ioſephs <hi>brethren were,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He ſpake no word but by Interpreter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At all unto them, and much did ſeeme</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A ſtranger to their language, as to them.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now he hath halfe his plot, and well content,</l>
               <l>Freely forgives them, whom he ſees repent.</l>
               <l>And in true token, he beginnes</l>
               <l>With teares to helpe them to bewayle their ſinnes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He weepes, returnes, and then as if he thought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas not enough they ſee and wayle their fault,</l>
               <l>As doth the grave Confeſſor uſe to doe;</l>
               <l>He means to put them to ſome pennance too.</l>
               <l>For having kept them three dayes in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Their comp'ny he diſmiſt, by one made leſſe.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Symeon</hi> before their eyes he ſent</l>
               <l>Bound backe againe to cloſe impriſonment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſure, this puniſhing of them did prove</l>
               <l>The truth of his forgiveneſſe, and his love,</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17029:37"/>
               <l>As did his acts of love in kindneſſe meant,</l>
               <l>Appeare to them a kind of puniſhment.</l>
               <l>For having given command that each mans ſack</l>
               <l>Be fil'd, and each mans coin reſtored back</l>
               <l>In their ſacks mouths: and likewiſe that they may</l>
               <l>Be furniſh'd with proviſion for their way.</l>
               <l>Forwards they ſet though with an heavy pace</l>
               <l>Clogg'd with their grief, and lamentable caſe.</l>
               <l>Sure tedious are their ſteps, who cannot ſtir</l>
               <l>But ſorrow is their fellow travellour.</l>
               <l>Sore griev'd in heart their journey they begun</l>
               <l>At their firſt lighting is confuſion.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> Ruben, <hi>that for provender unbinds</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſack the money in the mouth of't finds.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the clown that doth through medows paſſe</l>
               <l>Eſpying ſome glorious colours in the graſſe,</l>
               <l>Stoops down to reach them, being in hope to take:</l>
               <l>A goodly prize, when lo, he claſps a Snake.</l>
               <l>As pale as he was <hi>Reuben,</hi> when he ſaw</l>
               <l>His coyn in the ſacks mouth he doth withdraw</l>
               <l>His trembling hand, and in as great a feare</l>
               <l>As had he met the God of money there.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>See heer my coynes reſtor'd! cryes he, ſome train</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis for our lives, and we ſhall all be ſlain.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As in a field of ſtanding corn we find</l>
               <l>One end being ſhaken by the whisking wind,</l>
               <l>Thoſe which receive the guſt, declining fall</l>
               <l>Upon their neighbours, till clean thorough all</l>
               <l>Quivering runs; like to thoſe troubled ears,</l>
               <l>They ſhaken are with one anothers fears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh moſt unuſuall fright, For were not it</l>
               <l>Uoucht by Antiquity, and holy Writ,</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17029:37"/>
               <l>Who would in theſe our times of God ador'd</l>
               <l>Believe their fear: to ſee their gold reſtor'd.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Achan's</hi> heart upon th' accurſed touch</l>
               <l>Of the forbidden gold, faild half ſo much,</l>
               <l>Had his Fore-father's fears upon him fell</l>
               <l>T'had ſav'd a family in <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He fear'd not puniſhment, but it appears</l>
               <l>That they, alas! were puniſht with their feares,</l>
               <l>'Twas all God us'd as the correction mild,</l>
               <l>Of a good father to a loved child.</l>
               <l>And twas enough for he but ſhakes the rod,</l>
               <l>And ſtrait they fear, but 'twas the fear of God.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas! what iſt that God hath done they cry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto his ſervants: in this extaſie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They hom return to</hi> Canaan, <hi>and their tell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto their father all that them befell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saying, the man that is their Lord beſpake us</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In a rough language, and for ſpies did take us.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When ſorely troubled we, in humble wiſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anſwer'd, thy ſervants true men are, not ſpies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We of one aged father were begot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And were twelve brethren, whereof one is not.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The youngest as the comfort of his dayes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At home in</hi> Canaan <hi>with our father ſtayes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whereat the Lord unſatisfide replyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus ſhall your truth be prov'd to me, ariſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prevent your houſhold famine and be gone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With food ſufficient for you, leave but one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behind, but ſee that your return bring heer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your younger brother ſo ſhall it appear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You true men are, not ſpies, then Ile reſtore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your now detained brother, not before.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17029:38"/>
               <l>And if to tryall of your truth you'l ſtand,</l>
               <l>Do this and traffique with us in the Land,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> as yet ſtands mute, while they go on</l>
               <l>Emptying their ſacks of their proviſion.</l>
               <l>But when their money with their corn appears</l>
               <l>They ſtart, not having yet o'recome their fears:</l>
               <l>And lo this object, nothing leſſe diſmaid,</l>
               <l>The ſonnes, then now the ſire, they're all affraid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Iacob</hi> firſt the ſilence break, as one</l>
               <l>That in the grief challeng'd chief portion.</l>
               <l>He for his childrens loſſe, felt greateſt ſmart</l>
               <l>Which thus breaks forth, in agony of heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How hath your malice of my ſonnes bereft me</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph <hi>is not, nor</hi> Simeon <hi>is not left me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poor</hi> Benjamin <hi>you practice to betray,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with him take my ſouls delight away.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All theſe things are againſt me, heer he ſtaid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And gave his grief ſome vent: when <hi>Ruben</hi> ſaid</l>
               <l>Tis a hard ſtrait, we muſt for famine die,</l>
               <l>Or bring our brethren in this jeopardie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet let not</hi> Iſrael <hi>fear: let him but giue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Child into my hands, and we ſhall live</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let me enſure his life, and if he runnes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In any hazard, let it to my ſonnes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be ev'n alike; his ſafe return again</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Redeems their lives, or elſe let both be ſlain.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>More ſpake he, but in vain, <hi>Iacob</hi> is loth</l>
               <l>For his lov'd <hi>Benjamin,</hi> to accept them both</l>
               <l>A pledge, but with a diſcontented frown,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He tels them flat, my ſonne ſhall not go down</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Along with you, of</hi> Ioſeph <hi>I'm bereft</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This, only this, is all my comfort left</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſure 'twill bring (if any harm he have)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My gray hairs down with ſorrow to the grave.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17029:38"/>
            <head>THE FREE-MAN: OR, The ſixth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 43.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>Famine, that Mothers hath to kill</l>
               <l>Their ſonnes enforced, with a will</l>
               <l>As bad, doth <hi>Iſrael</hi> conſtraine</l>
               <l>To ſend his children downe againe</l>
               <l>With <hi>Benjamin:</hi> whoſe ſight hath wonne</l>
               <l>Liberty for <hi>Symeon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who now a free man with the reſt,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Ioſephs</hi> houſe partakes the feaſt.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>TWas a hard choyce,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> for his offence</l>
               <l>Had; between famine, Warre and Peſtilence.</l>
               <l>Not better much, was this of <hi>Iacobs</hi> here,</l>
               <l>To famiſh, or to part with what moſt deare</l>
               <l>Was to his ſoule: than which, no plague could be</l>
               <l>Of greater torment, not the miſery</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17029:39"/>
               <l>Warre brings along, not death, which as the chiefe</l>
               <l>Of humane terrors; ſo to dye for griefe,</l>
               <l>The worſt of deaths (as doubtleſſe he had done)</l>
               <l>His life ranne equall hazard with his ſonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Meane while, the brethren urging his conſent</l>
               <l>That <hi>Benjamin</hi> might goe, are diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Doubly to be refus'd, it did appeare</l>
               <l>Firſt, in his Fathers eye, that he more deare</l>
               <l>Was held than they; the ancient cauſe that bred</l>
               <l>Their hate to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he inherited</l>
               <l>As next of kinne: yet hence their ire did grow</l>
               <l>On better grounds, their brother might not goe,</l>
               <l>Though to ſave all their lives: in their diſtreſſe</l>
               <l>Their of-ſpring murmur'd in the wilderneſſe,</l>
               <l>Not more 'gainſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> then (their corn neer ſpent)</l>
               <l>They 'gainſt their Syre, who when he would have ſent</l>
               <l>Them down again: thus <hi>Iudah</hi> makes reply:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The man proteſted to us ſolemnly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To bring our brother, as we hop'd for grace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or favour, elſe we muſt not ſee his face.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So if you'l ſend him with us, well and good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We alſo will goe downe, and buy you food;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or elſe we will not: for he told us plaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without your brother, ſee me not againe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudges</hi> 77. <hi>King.</hi> 6.</note>A ſhrewd Dilemma! <hi>Iacob</hi> full as loath</l>
               <l>As the raſh <hi>Iephtah</hi> was to keepe his oath:</l>
               <l>Or as <hi>Samarias</hi> ſtarv'd Wyves, griev'd in heart</l>
               <l>To kill their ſonnes for food; was he to part</l>
               <l>With his lov'd <hi>Benjamin:</hi> oft they withdrew</l>
               <l>Their trembling hands, relenting ere they ſlew</l>
               <l>Their harmeleſſe babes, and oft they fild the skyes</l>
               <l>With bitter exclamations, and lowd cryes.</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17029:39"/>
               <l>So <hi>Iacobs</hi> love ere he could ſend his ſonne,</l>
               <l>Oft chang'd his wavering reſolution.</l>
               <l>His tenderneſſe and reaſon are at ſtrife,</l>
               <l>He ſhall not goe in perill of his life,</l>
               <l>The one alledgeth, t'other makes reply,</l>
               <l>If he goe not, he muſt for famine dye.</l>
               <l>Hee's now reſolv'd, yet ere he let him goe,</l>
               <l>He firſt takes liberty to vent his woe,</l>
               <l>And as an angry gameſter haſtily,</l>
               <l>Imputes ill fortune to the ſtanders by:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Iacobs</hi> wroth is for his loſſes bent</l>
               <l>On them for ought he knew were innocent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Why have you dealt ſo ill with me, in giving</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him knowledge you had yet a brother living?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Perhaps as deſperate men at point to dye,</l>
               <l>Thinke leſſe their danger, when with company,</l>
               <l>So you unto your fears could finde no other</l>
               <l>Eaſe or excuſe, but that you had a brother</l>
               <l>Yet to pertake your ſuffrings, if not ſo,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What reaſon had you elſe to let him know?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The man did ſtrictly of us they replide</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aske of our ſtate, and how we were allyde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If w'had more brethren or a Syre alive?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His jealouſie made him inquiſitive,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whil'ſt in the humbleſt way, our fear affords</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him anſwer to the tenour of his words:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For how alas! could we for truth have known</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He would have bid us bring our brother downe?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Iudah <hi>further to his father ſpake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And doth in feeling manner undertake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His brothers ſafety, and more boldly pleads</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their generall want of bread, which intercedes</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:17029:40"/>
               <l>A bad, but powerfull Advocate: O ſhall</l>
               <l>Your fonder love of one, deſtroy us all!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let the Lad goe, that we ſome food may bring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſave our little ones from famiſhing:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if into your hands I don't reſigne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him ſafe, his danger, and the blame be mine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had we not through your ſcruple lingred here,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We had return'd ere this, and quit your feare.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'T hath been a common and approved ſaw</l>
               <l>Throughout the world; Neceſſity hath no law,</l>
               <l>Yet I'me aſſur'd no Rhetorician can</l>
               <l>Plead halfe ſo well, for could there be in man,</l>
               <l>Till this his ſo neceſſitated tryall,</l>
               <l>An obſtinater ſpirit of denyall</l>
               <l>Than was in <hi>Iacob:</hi> who now yeelding, ſpake</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Iudah thus; if't muſt be ſo, then take</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Preſent of the beſt fruits of the land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And each mans money double in his hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For that which was return'd, which haply might</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have onely bin in you ſome overſight.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And take your brother alſo: riſe, and goe yee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And God Almighty give his mercy to yee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before the man, that ye may bring agen</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your other Brother, and my</hi> Benjamin:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For of my children, if I be bereav'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am beeeav'd.</hi> Here ſtopt he, they receiv'd</l>
               <l>Their charge with gladnes: cheerful now they went</l>
               <l>Without reply, their Father being content</l>
               <l>To ſend their brother with them, whom they hold</l>
               <l>A ſafeguard better, then the coyne twice told</l>
               <l>They brought along their honey, nor their ſpice,</l>
               <l>Their mirrhe, nor was their pretious Balm the price</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:17029:40"/>
               <l>Of <hi>Simeons</hi> ranſome: nothing elſe could be</l>
               <l>A witneſſe 'gainſt the Rulers jealouſie,</l>
               <l>Save <hi>Benjamin</hi> alone, 'gainſt <hi>Iacobs</hi> love</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iudah</hi> prevayles, when <hi>Ruben</hi> cannot move,</l>
               <l>Though better minded: as it doth appear</l>
               <l>By his firſt proffer of a pledge ſo dear</l>
               <l>As were his two ſonnes lives, which <hi>Iacob</hi> takes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iudah,</hi> but at <hi>Rubens</hi> hands forſakes.</l>
               <l>It ſure muſt grieve, him thus to be denide,</l>
               <l>That labour'd moſt againſt the fratricide,</l>
               <l>And ſale, th'imputed cauſe of all their wo:</l>
               <l>But 'tis no matter; ſo their brother go,</l>
               <l>Whoſe happier tongue perſwades; for him alone</l>
               <l>They for their peace and freedom build upon.</l>
               <l>Now they are confident, and travell faſt</l>
               <l>As hungry men for meat, then, midſt their haſt</l>
               <l>They make a ſudden ſtop: they ſee the Inne,</l>
               <l>Where when they laſt return'd, they'd frighted bin,</l>
               <l>In op'ning of their ſacks: they doubtfull are</l>
               <l>Leſt to their golden bait, ſome dang'rous ſnare</l>
               <l>Be fixt; and their coyn hidden in the ſack</l>
               <l>To pick a quarrell with them comming back.</l>
               <l>When having prov'd themſelves no ſpies to be,</l>
               <l>They might be charged now with thee very.</l>
               <l>Nor ſeems their <hi>Benjamin:</hi> but as one more</l>
               <l>(To be a bondman) then they brought before.</l>
               <l>For him doth <hi>Iudah's</hi> heart miſgive, his mind</l>
               <l>Is troubled for his pledges left behind,</l>
               <l>And for his fathers loſſe; and ſtill their fear</l>
               <l>Grows greater as to <hi>Egypt</hi> they draw near.</l>
               <l>At laſt conſidering that no ill they meant,</l>
               <l>Nor theft, nor falſhood was in their intent,</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17029:41"/>
               <l>As by their brothers comming is made plaine</l>
               <l>And bringing double money down again.</l>
               <l>Clearneſſe of conſcience doth a while beg in</l>
               <l>To comfort them: when lo their ancient ſinne</l>
               <l>Is interpos'd: me thinks, I cannot ſee</l>
               <l>Cryes one, yon Ruler, but my memory</l>
               <l>Afflicted is with <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> all his words</l>
               <l>Are full of terrour, and his eyes as ſwords</l>
               <l>Ev'n pierce my ſoule with fear: at ev'ry ſight</l>
               <l>Of him I tremble: ſo his looks affright,</l>
               <l>As had our brothers wronged ghoſt poſſeſt</l>
               <l>His brow, infuſing vengeance in his breſt.</l>
               <l>The ſame conceit troubles them all, they could</l>
               <l>Almoſt turn back: but hunger makes them bould,</l>
               <l>So that a little ha'ing o'recome their fear,</l>
               <l>Once more before the Ruler they appear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 25</note>As the hot wroth of <hi>David</hi> at the ſight</l>
               <l>And ſoft perſwaſion o' th' fair Carmelite,</l>
               <l>Melted away, when churliſh <hi>Nabal's</hi> life</l>
               <l>Was ſpar'd for the ſweet carriage of his wife.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> garbe is alt'red when he ſees</l>
               <l>Lov'd <hi>Benjamin,</hi> no ſhape of cruelties</l>
               <l>Can then uſurpe his brows: he bids prepare</l>
               <l>For now his brethren all invited are</l>
               <l>To feaſt with him at noon, yet ſtill their fear</l>
               <l>Miſconſters kindneſſe, ſure ſome plot is there</l>
               <l>They yet ſuſpect, and as they thought before</l>
               <l>Danger ith' coyn reſtor'd, now dread they more</l>
               <l>In this invitement, therefore to prevent</l>
               <l>(What they much doubted by this love was meant)</l>
               <l>Bondage: they to the Steward drawing neer</l>
               <l>Relate their ſtory, ſo in hope to clear,</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:17029:41"/>
               <l>And purge themſelves from guilt of all offence</l>
               <l>That might the anger of his Lord incenſe,</l>
               <l>And tendring double mony, they deny</l>
               <l>All knowledge by what means it came to lye</l>
               <l>In their ſacks mouths: when he that well did know</l>
               <l>His maſters mind, put on a fained ſhow</l>
               <l>Of wonder and ſaluting them with peace,</l>
               <l>Tels them their Fathers God gave that increaſe</l>
               <l>And treaſure in their ſacks; then going on</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>houſe, he brings forth</hi> Simeon</l>
               <l>They all are kindly us'd, as doth appear,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their feet are waſh'd, their beaſts have provender,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Two ſignes of welcome, yet amidſt their Feaſts</l>
               <l>They wanted ſome contentment of their beaſts.</l>
               <l>The ſilly jades ſeeing their racks ſtuft with meat</l>
               <l>Better then <hi>Canaan</hi> us'd them to, they eat</l>
               <l>Dreadleſſe of worſe event, when lo a fear</l>
               <l>Attends their maſters trenchers, drawing neere</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ioſephs</hi> table, they obſerve the noats</l>
               <l>Of the wiſe King, their knives are at their throats.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 23 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But now they find their entertainment free,</l>
               <l>Their brother <hi>Simeon</hi> too, at liberty,</l>
               <l>Their preſent well accepted, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> kind,</l>
               <l>Queſtions their welfare, ſatisfies his mind</l>
               <l>With news of <hi>Iacobs</hi> health: but when he ſees</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Benjamin</hi> ſtrange loving extaſies</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poſſeſſe him: now with hands impoſed on</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him cryes he, God be gracious to my ſonne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His bowels yearn, natures ſtrong ſympathy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Works out his melting heart into his eye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This was exceſſe of joy, that when he came</l>
               <l>From his loath'd priſon was not ſure the ſame.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:17029:42"/>
               <l>We read that then his face but once he clears,</l>
               <l>Which now twice waſht in water is and tears.</l>
               <l>He ſpake them fair, whilſt they as he foreſaid</l>
               <l>With lowly reverence, their obeyſance made.</l>
               <l>Much kindneſſe paſt, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> 'twould ſeem intends</l>
               <l>For his late churliſhneſſe to make amends.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſervants he commands to ſet on bread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now are three tables with all plenty ſpread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One for the</hi> Hebrews, <hi>one a board of ſtate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where</hi> Ioſeph <hi>all alone in's glory ſate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One for th'</hi> Egyptians, <hi>who to eat refuſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As an abomination with the</hi> Iews.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The brethren ſate in order, to their birth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to their youth, the place was fild with mirth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> Benjamin <hi>the beſt beloved gueſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had his meſſe ſeven times bigger then the reſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:17029:42"/>
            <head>THE PLEDGE: OR, The ſeventh Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 44.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>Fraid as their off-ſpring when purſude,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Pharoh</hi> and his multitude</l>
               <l>When they no means of ſcape could find</l>
               <l>The Sea before, the foe behind</l>
               <l>The Iſraelites are overtane,</l>
               <l>Iourneying homewards; theft was laine</l>
               <l>Vnto their charge: whilſt they deny</l>
               <l>In thought the guilt of felony,</l>
               <l>But when their ſacks they have unbound,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Benjamin</hi> the cup was found.</l>
               <l>They all return, and <hi>Iudah</hi> moves</l>
               <l>In his behalf, his fathers loves</l>
               <l>And life built on him, doth alledge,</l>
               <l>Offring himſelf to be his pledge.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Feaſt is ended: they with joy repleat</l>
               <l>(Their hearts wel cheer'd with welcom &amp; good meat</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:17029:43"/>
               <l>Think themſelues fit for travell, all their fears</l>
               <l>Forgot, none whiſpers in his brothers ears.</l>
               <l>Dreadleſſe of danger now they take their leaves</l>
               <l>Lowly ſubmiſſive, like the bowing ſheaves.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And part to lade their beaſts: while</hi> Ioſephs's <hi>brain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is plotting how to bring them back again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In every ſack the ſteward muſt reſtore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Again their moneyes as he did before.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> Benjamin, <hi>as was his ſhare i' th' feaſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſack ſev'n times more ſilver then the reſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is chardg'd with all: for there they had conveyd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Rulers ſilver Goblet, which betray'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Them to their fears a new, the diff'rence ſtrange</l>
               <l>Twixt his exceedings is: and ſad the change.</l>
               <l>He at the table ſitting down a gueſt</l>
               <l>Receiv'd a ſeven-fold portion of the feaſt,</l>
               <l>As of his brethrens terrour now, he bare</l>
               <l>The love away then, now the ſorrows are</l>
               <l>In as full meaſure given to him: but why,</l>
               <l>Youle wonder, the pretended felony</l>
               <l>To him alone was laid, or why ſhould he</l>
               <l>The greateſt ſharer in their torment be</l>
               <l>That was not guilty of their crime? to try</l>
               <l>Heer <hi>Ioſeph</hi> wiſely meant their amity,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Theod. q. <hi>105.</hi> in Gen.</note>Or if their love was greater that they bore</l>
               <l>To's brother now, then to himſelf before;</l>
               <l>How they that had him thither ſold could be</l>
               <l>Content with <hi>Benjamins</hi> captivity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whether twere ſo, or whether for the grief</l>
               <l>They put him to, or for their unbelief</l>
               <l>He meant this purgatory, the ſame pains</l>
               <l>Of ſoule that there are faign'd to purge the ſtains</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:17029:43"/>
               <l>Of bad mens lives afflicts them, their offence</l>
               <l>Gnaws them with the ſame worme of conſcience.</l>
               <l>For ſtill as oft as they have cauſe to fear</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is remembred with a tear</l>
               <l>And ſtill he gives them cauſe, a puniſhment</l>
               <l>As great, as juſt revenge could ere invent,</l>
               <l>Is ſuch a fear, the quinteſcence and chief</l>
               <l>Of woe, the very ſoule and ſence of grief.</l>
               <l>The plagues of Hell are horrour,<note place="margin">Greg. ho. <hi>22.</hi> in Ezek.</note> and mans fear</l>
               <l>Is a perſpective through which leen appear,</l>
               <l>All dangers greater, death it ſelf 'tis clear</l>
               <l>Brings no more tetrour with it then our fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Torment of mercy! thus our maker proves</l>
               <l>His childrens patience, vexing whom he loves,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his brethren; who the day</l>
               <l>Of their departure broak, now take their way</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Towards</hi> Canan <hi>with their loads: ſcarce had they paſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The City walls: when lo in all poſt haſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their friend the ſteward or' takes them with a face</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bewraying choller, bids them ſlack their pace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>They in obedience anſwer'd him, and ſtood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whilſt he, why have you thus paid ill for good</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eagerly charg'd them? iſt not that (quoth he)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The cup he drinks in, 'tis a robbery</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſt ſacrilegious (not to be excus'd)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It was the ſame he in divining us'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ill have yee done: alas! what could they ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What could they think, when he that yeſterday</l>
               <l>Us'd them ſo well? ſhould to their charge impute</l>
               <l>Theft now; and make a ſlander his ſalute.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lo heer an Embleme of man's life! their fears</l>
               <l>Give way to comfort, and anon appears</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:17029:44"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4</note>New cauſe of trembling: joy ſucceedeth ſadneſſe,</l>
               <l>And unto them that grieve, is promis'd gladneſſe.</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt with wonder, now their looks deſcry</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 21.</note>Them like good <hi>Naboath,</hi> charg'd with blaſphemy.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Why, ſaith my Lord, theſe words? our God forbid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We ere ſhould do this thing: the money hid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In our ſacks mouth from</hi> Canaan <hi>we brought back</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How ſhould we then, or gold, or ſilver take</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By ſtealth from thy Lords houſe? ſo let it be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With whom ſoe're of us 'tis found, that he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May die the death, and we do all accord</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To yeeld our ſelves as priſoners to thy Lord.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The motion's good, right did his purpoſe ſpeed</l>
               <l>That well knew where 'twas laid, and ſoon agreed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Only the man with whom tis found ſhall be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ſervant: all the reſt of you go free.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All parties are well pleas'd, when not afraid</l>
               <l>But full as confident of what they ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 12.</note>As <hi>David</hi> anſwering <hi>Nathan:</hi> or that wretch</l>
               <l>That made of councell 'gainſt himſelf did teach</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heſter</hi> 6.</note>
                  <hi>His foes preferment: ſpeedily they take</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their ſacks down to the ground, and make</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A buſie ſearch, with th' eldeſt they begin</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And end where it was found with</hi> Benjamin.</l>
               <l>Who bluſht, though not for guilt, his face the ſame</l>
               <l>Was as his brothers courted by his dame.</l>
               <l>So look'd they all as the ſtones rol'd away</l>
               <l>The five Kings hid ith' cave of <hi>Mackedah,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beheld the victor: ſhame of their diſgrace</l>
               <l>Sits heavy on their brow, and burns their face</l>
               <l>They plead not guilty: and as if they meant</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſhew their hearts how true they were, they rent</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:17029:44"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their cloaths to their bare breaſts: but 'tis no ſeaſon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To vent their paſſions, now, they yeeld to reaſon,</l>
               <l>How to redeem their brother, each mans ſack</l>
               <l>Burthens his Aſſe, and all to town go back.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>By this is</hi> Iudah <hi>and his brethren come</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Ioſephs <hi>houſe, (for he was yet at home)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before him to the ground they fall, when he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As one unkindely dealt with: why have ye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus us'd me asks? or what is this y' have done</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In recompence of my affection?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had you a hope you might eſcape me ſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or could you be ſo ign'rant not to know</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I could divine? what anſwer have you left?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or may ſo vilde and impudent a theft</l>
               <l>Finde an excuſe? or have you yet the face</l>
               <l>To uſe denyall in ſo plaine a caſe?</l>
               <l>Iudah <hi>replyes, (my Lord) what can we ſay?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What ſhall we ſpeake? how may we wipe away</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This guilt? (and then as men in feare confeſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More then they know, ſo they ſeeing no redreſſe</l>
               <l>In juſtifying of themſelves, they yeeld</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To the apparant proofes) God hath reveald</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th'iniquity of thy ſervants; we are bound</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy ſervants, we, and he with whom 'twas found.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay, God forbid, ſaith</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>onely he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With whom the Cup was found, is bound to me;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With you I've nought to doe, you fears may ceaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You to your Father may returne in peace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mercy is that whereby Gods goodneſſe bends</l>
               <l>To humane conference; God by that extends</l>
               <l>Mans boldneſſe to ſollicit him, and ſo</l>
               <l>As <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God gracious made him know</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:17029:45"/>
               <l>Counſels divine, and the allotted fate</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.</note>Of curſed <hi>Sodome,</hi> growes importunate.</l>
               <l>In like ſort <hi>Iudah</hi> at the ſoft reply</l>
               <l>Of milder <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> courage takes thereby:</l>
               <l>His caſe addes boldneſſe too, for's brothers ſake,</l>
               <l>His Fathers, and his ſonnes lives, all at ſtake:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Lord (ſaith he) and freely drawing neere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Craves leave to tell his ſtory in his care.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Prov.</note>The wiſe Proverbialiſt compares the ire</l>
               <l>Of moved Kings, to a conſuming fire.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No leſſe did</hi> Iudah <hi>take it for, oh thou</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That eu'n as</hi> Pharoh <hi>art! ah let not now</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thine anger burne againſt thy ſervants! we</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When we laſt came were asked, have not yee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Father, or a Brother? when in briefe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We told the truth of all (alas the griefe!)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We ſaid we had a Father, whoſe gray head</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Was by a tender ſtripling comforted:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſonne of his old age; and this alone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did make him youthfull; having now but one,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Endeared him the more) of his loved Mother,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This the ſole relict, having loſt his brother:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou badſt thy ſervants bring him downe to thee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That thou might'ſt ſee him, when (my Lord) ſaid we,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He may not leave his Father, ſhould they part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It were enough to breake the old mans heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still layd'ſt thou thy commands, to ſee thy face</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No more, unleſſe our brother were in place.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So to our Father we delivered plaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy words, and when he bad us goe againe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To buy a little food, we let him know,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without our brother, that we could not goe.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17029:45"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>To which thy ſervant, the old mans oplyde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye know my wife bare me two ſonnes, one dy'de,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He went out from me, but return'd no more;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some beaſt I therefore ſaid, in pieces tore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That comfort from me, if you therefore take</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His brother too, and any harme o'retake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Lad, 'twill bring (but heav'n him ſhield and ſave,)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My gray hayres downe with ſorrow to the grave.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe twayne his ages play-fellowes, as deare</l>
               <l>And pretious to him as his eye-bals were:</l>
               <l>Whereof one gone, if t'other loſe it's light,</l>
               <l>Then is it time to bid the world good-night.</l>
               <l>And well might <hi>Iacob</hi> love him, whom the paine</l>
               <l>And hardeſt labour of his youth did gaine:</l>
               <l>Twice ſeven cold winters, twice ſeven ſummers heat,</l>
               <l>With patience he endur'd, ere he could get</l>
               <l>Their much lov'd Mother, and as long againe</l>
               <l>It was, ere could his prayrs and teares obtaine</l>
               <l>This of-ſpring more then all their brothers priz'd</l>
               <l>For them his faith, and works were exercis'd,</l>
               <l>Their purchaſe was not by his toyle alone,</l>
               <l>They were the fruit of his devotion.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If we returne without him, 'twill deſtroy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Fathers life, that's bound up in the boy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So to the grave, downe ſhall thy ſervants bring</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Syre thy ſervants grey-head ſorrowing.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy ſervant ſurety for the Lad became</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto my Father, mine ſhall be the blame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ever if I bring him not againe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then let thy ſervant ſo much grace obtaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That I may for the Lad thy bondman be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And he with's brethren goe, inſtead of me.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:17029:46"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>For how ſhall I goe up without the Lad?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be a witneſſe, and ſpectator ſad</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There of my Fathers ſuffrings for my ſake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who for the childes returne did undertake.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:17029:46"/>
            <head>THE DISCOVERY: OR, The eighth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 45.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>Here like a reconciled Lover,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> weeping, doth diſcover</l>
               <l>In teares of kindneſſe to his brother</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, unable yet to ſmother</l>
               <l>His paſsions longer; five he brings</l>
               <l>Of them to Court, who by the Kings</l>
               <l>Directions, and commandement,</l>
               <l>With Chariots are for <hi>Iacob</hi> ſent.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THus long good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with an unmov'd eare,</l>
               <l>The dolefull ſtory of himſelfe did heare</l>
               <l>His Fathers love and teares: he that denyes</l>
               <l>The ſtrength of nature in her ſympathies:</l>
               <l>Had he ſeen <hi>Ioſeph</hi> here ſad burthen keep,</l>
               <l>To his griev'd fathers groanes, or heard him weep</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:17029:47"/>
               <l>For love to <hi>Benjamin,</hi> his error he</l>
               <l>Had ſure deteſted as an hereſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a naturall ſonne appeares in this,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Iacobs</hi> griefes are parents unto his.</l>
               <l>So like his paſſions, to his Syres, I finde,</l>
               <l>As had he with his body, got his minde.</l>
               <l>He cannot of his Fathers ſorrowes heare,</l>
               <l>But as ſad iſſue, it begets a teare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ow dull were all his brethren? not to know</l>
               <l>Him weeping now, as he was wont to doe:</l>
               <l>He look'd as when they ſold him; ſalt drops ſhrowd</l>
               <l>The Majeſty of's eyes, as when a clowd</l>
               <l>So dimmes the radiant brightneſſe of the Sunne,</l>
               <l>That weakeſt ſights may boldly gaze upon</l>
               <l>His beames: what miſts doe paſſions caſt before</l>
               <l>Our eyes? their envy did not blinde them more</l>
               <l>From knowing of their brother, that in teares</l>
               <l>Beg'd for his life; then now again their fears</l>
               <l>Darken both ſoules and bodies, both their eyes,</l>
               <l>Their underſtandings, and their memories;</l>
               <l>They think not what his dreams foretold, his place</l>
               <l>Of promis'd greatneſſe, nor their humble caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mens hearts 'gainſt dangers oft miſgive, and ſome</l>
               <l>Are light before againſt a joy to come:</l>
               <l>But no ſuch motions in their hearts doe ſtir,</l>
               <l>To make them know this their deliverer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blinde fathers of as blinde a race! whom ſo</l>
               <l>Not all the Prophecies could make to know</l>
               <l>Their deare redeemer, whom they us'd with more</l>
               <l>Malice than did their Syres his type before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſhew his love, Gods ever bleſſed Sonne</l>
               <l>Shed teares of griefe, and of compaſſion:</l>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:17029:47"/>
               <l>We never read he ſmild: ſo <hi>Ioſeph</hi> here</l>
               <l>Cannot expreſſe his joy, but with a teare.</l>
               <l>Both paſſions finde one vent, both flowing ran</l>
               <l>From's eyes, as if they melted had the man.</l>
               <l>So ſtrove they for precedence, and t' o'recome</l>
               <l>Each other, as the twins in's Grandames wombe,</l>
               <l>Which firſt ſhould iſſue forth, he hears with griefe</l>
               <l>His Fathers fears and ſorrows, and beliefe</l>
               <l>Of his deceaſe; but now o're-joy'd agen,</l>
               <l>He weeps to ſee his brother <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The eye is the ſoules index; had you ſeen</l>
               <l>The Brethren plotting a revenge, their ſpleen</l>
               <l>Did in their eyes appear, and you might ſpy</l>
               <l>The innocence of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his eye,</l>
               <l>As here his love: could their hard hearts have ſo</l>
               <l>Melted as <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> to conceive the woe</l>
               <l>Of their ſad Father, or their bowels yearne,</l>
               <l>And nature, ſpite of ſpleen, made them diſcern</l>
               <l>Their brother, it had ſav'd their preſent fears,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſorrows, and good <hi>Ioſephs</hi> tears;</l>
               <l>Which now as Lectures are to them; and all</l>
               <l>That diſobedient, or unnaturall</l>
               <l>Unto their Parents, or their brethren be,</l>
               <l>Inſtructing them in love and piety.</l>
               <l>The goodneſſe of his nature, is a plaine</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doctrinall preſident, he can't refraine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before the ſtanders by, ſome drops muſt ſlide</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E're he commands convenience; none abide</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now with him, but his brethren, when in tears</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He makes them know their</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>and appears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ever their demerits might him move</l>
               <l>In his own likeneſſe, and a brothers love.</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:17029:48"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>He weeps aloud, till all that preſent were</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Pharohs <hi>houſe, and all th' Egyptians heare.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Kings</hi> 19.</note>God comforting <hi>Eliah,</hi> firſt with flame,</l>
               <l>Strong tearing winds, &amp; hideous ſtorms, there came,</l>
               <l>Ere the ſtill voyce was heard; ſo if I dare</l>
               <l>Th' immediate actions of the Lord compare</l>
               <l>With thoſe he works by agents; comfort here</l>
               <l>Came to the brethren, as t' <hi>Eliah</hi> there.</l>
               <l>For after frownes, high words and cryes were paſt</l>
               <l>In milder tearmes he lets them know at laſt</l>
               <l>'Tis I am <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> doth my Father live?</l>
               <l>When loe his brethren could no anſwer give,</l>
               <l>And can you blame them for it? ſhould you ſee</l>
               <l>One long deceas'd, at leaſt ſo thought to be,</l>
               <l>Appeare before you, full as much remaine</l>
               <l>They troubled at his preſence; who again</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cals them, come neer I pray you, and being come</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tells them, I am your brother</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>whom</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You into</hi> Aegypt <hi>ſold: yet doe not grieve,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor be you angry with your ſelves, beleeve</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By Gods decree you ſold me, I was ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before you to provide you nouriſhment,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to preſerve your lives: but two yeers paſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are of the famine, which as yet muſt laſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Five more, in which by Gods moſt firme decree,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There neither earing ſhall, nor harveſt be:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haſte therefore to my Father, ſay thus ſaid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph <hi>thy ſonne; God me a Lord hath made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O're</hi> Aegypt, <hi>wherefore come thou downe to me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And tarry not, ſo ſhall thy dwelling be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Goſhen, <hi>where the land is fat and good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for convenience in my neighbourhood.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:17029:48"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>There ſhall thy ſonnes and thy ſonnes ſonnes be plac'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy numerous flocks and heards and all thou haſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There will I nouriſh thee, for yet remayn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Five years of famine; leſt for want of grain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou and thy houſhold all the ſoules that be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Born of thy loyns ſhould come to poverty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My brothers eyes have ſeen, ſo likewiſe ſee yee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It is my mouth that ſpeaks theſe words unto yee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yee therefore to my Father ſhall relate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The glory yee have ſeen, and all my ſtate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Egypt; <hi>yee ſhall haſten and be gone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To bring my Father down unto his ſonne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To exemplifie Gods love, the holy writ</l>
               <l>The love of woman doth compare to it.</l>
               <l>Which love is full of fervency, ſo this</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heer</hi> Benjamin, <hi>and he embrace, and kiſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And weep, and on each others necks they fall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He weeps again, and now he kiſt them all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Between theſe loves this difference may ſuffice</l>
               <l>That love hath melting lips, this melting eyes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In teares they held their conference, whilſt report</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had noys'd the fame thereof through all the Court.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis news in</hi> Pharoh's <hi>houſe; and lo the thing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleas'd all that heard it, for it pleas'd the King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who thus beſpake him: to thy brethren ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Go lade your beaſts, get home, and bring away</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your father and your houſholds: I will give</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fat of</hi> Egypt <hi>to you, cat and live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I have commanded you, now therefore take<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Waggons throughout the land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>make</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All fit for travell, now forget your home,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bring father, wives, and little ones, and come.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:17029:49"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haſten away, regard you not your ſtuff,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The good of</hi> Egypt's <hi>yours, be that enough.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> Iſraels <hi>children went, and</hi> Ioſeph <hi>made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Waggons, and all things fit (as</hi> Pharoh <hi>bad)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For them to travell with, he cloah'd them in</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>New change of rayment; but to</hi> Benjamin</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Three hundred pieces he of ſilver gave</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſides five change of rayment, much more brave</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then were the reſt, and to his Father he</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In this wiſe ſent: ten Aſſes laden be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With the good things of</hi> Egypt, <hi>beſides corn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And bread, and meat, by ten ſhe-aſſes born</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſerve his Father by the way, and ſo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He ſet his brethren forth; but ere they go</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He gives a peacefull caveat: bids them ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That by the way they do not diſagree.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well might he give the charge, whom once their hate</l>
               <l>Left to his death, or to a worſer fate:</l>
               <l>But that great Providence that rules each ſtarre</l>
               <l>Who gave to them their influence, whoſe are</l>
               <l>All powers of Heav'n and Earth, whoſe firm decree</l>
               <l>Is Natures Law, and humane deſtiny.</l>
               <l>That power him ſerves, did not pow'r him ſave,</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might have liv'd and dy'de a ſlave.</l>
               <l>But now as men that truly did repent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of what they'd done, they heard his words, and went</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Forth out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and by this they gather</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neer to the land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>to their Father.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where as the bringers of good news they ſtriue</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which firſt ſhall make it known,</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>alive,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And governs</hi> Egypt; <hi>then at large they ſpeak</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of all his ſtate; but</hi> Iacobs <hi>faith is weak.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:17029:49"/>
               <l>As men to melancholly giv'n delight</l>
               <l>In ſadder tales, to feed the appetite,</l>
               <l>Of their dull humour; ſo was his belief</l>
               <l>To all things hard, that did gainſay his grief,</l>
               <l>Now grown in him a habit: ſince he deem'd</l>
               <l>This his dear <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt; for heer it ſeem'd</l>
               <l>He thought his childrens meaning was t'abuſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him with vain hopes; and fainteth at the news.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But then declar'd they to him</hi> Ioſephs <hi>words,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And all he ſaid unto them, this affords</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some better ground for hope; but when he ſees</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The waggons that were ſent, as by degrees</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His fainting ſpirit in him did revive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So his beleef encreaſt,</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>alive!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph's <hi>my ſonne, it is enough; for I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will yet go down, and ſee him ere I die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:17029:50"/>
            <head>THE MEETING: OR, The ninth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 46.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſacrifice and prayers,</l>
               <l>God by night to him appears</l>
               <l>With comfort; fearleſſe he along</l>
               <l>Iourneys; ſeven and threeſcore ſtrong</l>
               <l>Of his own loyns begot; their meeting,</l>
               <l>And paſsions of their joyfull greeting:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his brethren doth adviſe,</l>
               <l>How to the King to make replyes.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw do the tents of <hi>Iſrael</hi> abound</l>
               <l>With mirth and gladnes, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt is found.</l>
               <l>So the ſtray'd ſheep which lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſhepheard ſought,</l>
               <l>Did cheer the finder; ſo the womans groat:</l>
               <l>So pleas'd our heav'nly Father is to winne</l>
               <l>A ſonne to mercy, that was loſt by ſinne.</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:17029:50"/>
               <l>Old <hi>Iacob</hi> heard not with a greater joy</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rachell</hi> had made him father of a boy</l>
               <l>Then now this news; when with a gladſome heart,</l>
               <l>He with his ſonnes, and ſubſtance did depart</l>
               <l>Towards the land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> heretofore,</l>
               <l>He long'd not to embrace the mother more,</l>
               <l>Then now to kiſſe her ſonne: yet can no haſt,</l>
               <l>No ſtrong deſire hurry him on ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>But to his fathers God heel make ſome ſtay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He offer'd ſacrifice, when in his way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He took</hi> Beerſheba; <hi>where the Lord appear'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In viſions of the night, and</hi> Iacob <hi>heard</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Name twice cald upon; he makes reply</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto the holy voice, lo heer am I,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So holy <hi>Abraham</hi> anſwer'd;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen,</hi> 32.11. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.3.</note> ſo ſhould all</l>
               <l>Gods ſervants be as ready at his call.</l>
               <l>Chriſts ſheep do his voice, and him purſue</l>
               <l>And 'tis undoubtedly a ſigne moſt true</l>
               <l>Of guilt, or diſobedience, when wee</l>
               <l>With <hi>Adam</hi> hide us, or with <hi>Ionas</hi> flee</l>
               <l>When he cals on us, firſt at the laſt day</l>
               <l>The juſt ſhall riſe; and anſwer here are they.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſſ,</hi> 4.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They that expect good tydings, give good eare,</l>
               <l>And ready are, as <hi>Iacob</hi> was to hear</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What God ſpake further to him; I am hee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy father ſerv'd, and I will make of thee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A mighty Nation: therfore do not fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Go down to</hi> Egypt, <hi>I will bleſſe thee there:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With thee will I go down, with thee remayn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I will alſo bring thee up again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'le bleſſe thee whilſt thou liv'ſt, and when thou dies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph <hi>ſhall put his hand upon thine eyes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:17029:51"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heer</hi> Iacob <hi>roſe with comfort, when his ſonnes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had plac'd him with their wives and little ones</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Pharoh's <hi>chariots, then with all their ſtore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their goods and cattle they from</hi> Canaan <hi>bore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They left</hi> Beerſheba, Iacob <hi>and his ſeed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſonnes, and his ſonnes ſonnes, and all their breed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A goodly progeny to</hi> Egypt <hi>came</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where God made good the bleſſing of his<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12.</note> name,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He brought down with him as the text enrowls</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of his own loyns begotten threeſcore ſouls</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſix, which were in</hi> Egypt <hi>made up ten,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> Ioſeph <hi>and his wife and children.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had <hi>Sarah</hi> liv'd to ſee this fair foundation,</l>
               <l>Her ſelf the root of this ſo forward Nation,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iſrael.</note>She that miſdoubting ſmil'd, would at this ſight</l>
               <l>So farre above her faith, have laught out-right.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> is well increas'd that went but one,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Padan Aram,</hi> with his ſtaffe alone,</l>
               <l>Returns inricht with wives, and concubines,</l>
               <l>Twelve hopefull ſonnes begotten of his loyns</l>
               <l>Children, and flocks, and heards, all that his eye</l>
               <l>Could wiſh to ſee, a goodly progenie,</l>
               <l>But they by this are to ſo many grown</l>
               <l>As nature could by propagation</l>
               <l>Bring forth, twelve families are made of one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lo heer, and ſee with wonder the increaſe,</l>
               <l>Of them, whom God hath once begun to bleſſe,</l>
               <l>Full well deſerves it, <hi>Moſes</hi> for a Scribe,</l>
               <l>They go by families, but return by Tribes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſtill obſerve how God his word doth keep</l>
               <l>And what he promis'd <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his ſleep,</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:17029:51"/>
               <l>Payes to him waking; all the ſheafs muſt bend</l>
               <l>The Sun, the Moon, and the 'lev'n ſtars deſcend</l>
               <l>To do him honour: they by this draw neer</l>
               <l>To <hi>Egypt, Iudah</hi> is their harbinger.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He to prepare a place doth foremoſt go,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And comes to</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>houſe whom he lets know,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their fathers neer approch, who at the news</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sets forth to meet him: mark their interviews,</l>
               <l>They ſtudy no ſet ſpeech, their love prevents</l>
               <l>Common ſalutes, and formall complements:</l>
               <l>But like two foes, who long at deadly fewd</l>
               <l>With zeale of hate each others lives purſude,</l>
               <l>Now well appointed meet, their eager ſpight</l>
               <l>Admits no parly to delay their fight.</l>
               <l>Their bloudy thoughts are painted in their face</l>
               <l>And ſhown with terrour in a rough embrace.</l>
               <l>The paſſions differ, would I could as well</l>
               <l>Find love enough to make a paralell:</l>
               <l>But ſeldome doth that better paſſion move</l>
               <l>Two friends, to ſuch an extaſie of love</l>
               <l>As theſe: ſo ſhall the joyfull bodies come</l>
               <l>To meet their bleſt ſouls in <hi>Elizium,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Save that ſuch perfect happineſſe could ne're</l>
               <l>Admit the badge of ſorrow; we in tears</l>
               <l>Expreſſe the height of gladneſſe, as if 'twere</l>
               <l>To intimate, no Joy is perfect here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As in the bodies temper it hath bin</l>
               <l>Truly obſerv'd which are then moſt hot within</l>
               <l>When outwardly we freeze; ev'n ſo we find</l>
               <l>As much deceit in ſymptomes of the mind,</l>
               <l>Great ſorrows ſeldom weep, and yet appears</l>
               <l>In the exceſſe of humane gladneſſe, tears.</l>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:17029:52"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> that ever ſince his ſonne was loſt</l>
               <l>Had us'd his eyes to nothing elſe, accoſts</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him with a wonted ſhowre, which from his eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dropt on his neck; he that did ſympathize</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In all his father's paſſions can't refrain</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But pays him with as many tears again</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They breath their ſouls in ſigh's, their kiſſes dry</l>
               <l>Their moyſtned cheeks; then in an extaſie</l>
               <l>Iacob <hi>cryes out (preſt with his ſonnes embrace)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now let me die, ſince I have ſeen thy face</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thou art yet alive: So holy</hi> Paul</l>
               <l>In heavenly contemplation, fil'd with all</l>
               <l>Thoſe joyes his faith preſented him, deſires</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip</hi> 1.23.</note>To be diſſolv'd; his ſoule to Heav'n aſpires</l>
               <l>Or would before its time; but that kept in</l>
               <l>It cannot for the fleſhly walls of ſin,</l>
               <l>From whence he prayes for freedom; <hi>Iacobs</hi> thought</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12.</note>From earth to heaven ſure like his ladder wrought.</l>
               <l>As twere made mindfull by this happineſſe</l>
               <l>Of what unſpeakable delights do bleſſe</l>
               <l>Good ſoules departed, he with <hi>Paul</hi> doth cry</l>
               <l>Tranſported with his joy, now let me die.</l>
               <l>Twas a good wiſh, he, when what moſt on earth</l>
               <l>Might glad his ſoule (and make him wiſh new birth,</l>
               <l>To live another age) befell, doth crave.</l>
               <l>A peaceable departure to his grave.</l>
               <l>Whence learn, no bleſſing may on earth be given</l>
               <l>But a good man hath better hopes in heaven.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whoſe paſſions could not elſe be orecome</l>
               <l>Turns from his Father to his brethen, whom</l>
               <l>He thus beſpake; I will to <hi>Pharoh</hi> go</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To whom my fathers comming I will ſhow,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:17029:52"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>And yours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I'le tell him that ye ſhepheards are,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Men that have ben train'd up to have the care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of Flocks and Heards, which ye along have brought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſave from famine, if he aske you ought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When ye before him come, be my words made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſame: thus ſhall ye ſay, thy ſervants trade</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hath been 'bout cattell, from our youth till now:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ours, and our Fathers; ſo ſhall he endow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You with the Land of</hi> Goſhen, <hi>a good place</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Free to your ſelves, and to your flocks to graze</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without diſturbance; yours ſhall be alone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The land: for an abhomination</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your trade is to th' Egyptians, ſo ſhall ye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have to your ſelves the fruitfull <hi>Goſhen</hi> free.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:17029:53"/>
            <head>THE PVRCHACE: OR, The tenth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 47.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>By his Favourites endearement,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharoh</hi> welcome, and preferment</l>
               <l>Gave to <hi>Iacob</hi> and his ſonnes:</l>
               <l>To them, their wives, and little ones,</l>
               <l>He doth the land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> give,</l>
               <l>There with their Flocks and Heards to live.</l>
               <l>They onely of the famine ſtand</l>
               <l>Fearleſſe, whil'ſt th' Egyptians land,</l>
               <l>Cattle, and ev'ry pretious thing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> purchas'd for the King:</l>
               <l>Except o'th Prieſts, whom he allowd</l>
               <l>A daily competence of food.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>IMagine <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hath by this time told</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Fathers comming, to the King: behold</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:17029:53"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Brethren with their flocks, and the old man</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Father, are come downe from</hi> Canaan,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Driv'n thence by famine, late they did arrive</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In fruitfull</hi> Goſhen, <hi>here of them are five.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then to the King he brought his brethren on,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who queſtions them their occupation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As</hi> Ioſeph <hi>taught them, they their anſwer made,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We Shepheards are, 'thath bin our Fathers trade</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Time out of minde, encourag'd by the ſoyle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which like to <hi>Eden</hi> Garden, without toyle,</l>
               <l>Yeelded content and plenty, but diſtreſt</l>
               <l>With famine now, ſeems curſed, as the reſt</l>
               <l>Of the whole earth, for our firſt Parents ſinne.</l>
               <l>'Tis thou alone art happy, that within</l>
               <l>Thy realmes, men onely of Gods mercies ſing</l>
               <l>Pſalmes, and not Lamentations: Let O King!</l>
               <l>His goodneſſe teach thee pitty us, whil'ſt we</l>
               <l>Thy ſervants and thy ſubjects crave to be.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We are come downe to ſojourne in thy land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Humbly deſiring thou wilt give command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We may in</hi> Goſhen <hi>live. The King replyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph, <hi>thy Father is come downe, thine eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold the land, ſee where thou find'ſt the beſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There let thy Father and thy brethren reſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let them in</hi> Goſhen <hi>dwell: and if there be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amongſt them, any whoſe activity</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Surmounts their fellows, skilfull in their trade,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let them be rulers o're my cattell made.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At firſt ſight, good encouragement they heard,</l>
               <l>Not onely being admitted, but prefer'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> Ioſephs <hi>ſake, who now his Father brought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſet him before</hi> Pharoh: <hi>ſo we ought</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:17029:54"/>
               <l>When God doth bleſſe us thankfull hearts to bring</l>
               <l>And bleſſe again, as <hi>Iacob</hi> bleſt the King,</l>
               <l>Who tooke good notice of him, it appears</l>
               <l>By his demands, he queſtions him his years.</l>
               <l>To whom thus <hi>Iacob,</hi> in whoſe ſober eye</l>
               <l>Did reverence appeare, and gravity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The dayes and yeares of this my pilgrimage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A hundred are and thirty, a ſhort age</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Compar'd to that my Fathers lived in,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But few and evill, all my dayes have bin.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He firſt was ſenſible how life began</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3</note>To ſhorten, ſince God left to ſtrive with man:</l>
               <l>For he the firſt of all to me appears,</l>
               <l>Complaining for the fewneſſe of his yeares.</l>
               <l>How ſhould we ſcan our lives, if <hi>Iacob</hi> doe</l>
               <l>Confeſſe his dayes but ſhort and evill too?</l>
               <l>Whom God choſe in the womb, who by his mother</l>
               <l>The bleſſing gate, and birth-right from his brother,</l>
               <l>Whom God ſo oft confer'd with, who did ſtand</l>
               <l>On his lam'd legge, and with a claſped hand,</l>
               <l>Graſpt't God himſelfe, and wraſtling overcame,</l>
               <l>Winning the prize, a bleſſing, and a<note n="*" place="margin">Iſraell.</note> name;</l>
               <l>If he found ill in his dayes, how ſhall we</l>
               <l>Lift up eyes, moſt gratious God to thee?</l>
               <l>Yet thou like <hi>Pharoh</hi> us that ſtrangers are,</l>
               <l>Nay worſe, thine enemies; doſt not onely ſpare</l>
               <l>Succour, and cheriſh, but promot'ſt us high</l>
               <l>To crowne and Kingdomes of eternity.</l>
               <l>Grant then, O God, that for thy mercy, we</l>
               <l>May ever more continue prayſing thee:</l>
               <l>As holy <hi>Iacob</hi> with a loyall heart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did bleſsing</hi> Pharoh <hi>till he did depart</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:17029:54"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Out of his preſence, and with</hi> Ioſeph <hi>went</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who'cording to the Kings commandement</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gave him and his the beſt part to poſſeſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Egypt, <hi>ev'n the Land of</hi> Ramaſes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where them he plentifully ſtor'd and fed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>According to their families with bread</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which every where was ſcarce; in</hi> Egypt, <hi>and</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Canaan <hi>that milk and hony flowing land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The famine rageth ſore, ſtill</hi> Pharoh <hi>bleſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Ioſeſph</hi> is: the treaſury increaſt</l>
               <l>And where but titulary Kings the throne</l>
               <l>Held heretofore, <hi>Egypt</hi> is <hi>Pharohs</hi> own.</l>
               <l>For yet the famine laſting and the ſoyle</l>
               <l>Ingratefull to the painfull husbands toyle,</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſlymy <hi>Nilus</hi> could not make it bear</l>
               <l>Their purſes empty as their bellies were:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Coyn was as ſcarce as corn, when wanting gold</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For food, their horſes, and their herds they ſold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which in one conſum'd to</hi> Pharoh's <hi>hands</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Being maſters now of nothing elſe, their lands</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And their poor ſelves they do as bondmen yeild,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And every man for corn doth ſell his field</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till</hi> Egypt <hi>all was</hi> Pharohs: <hi>they forſake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Country-houſes, and themſelves betake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To dwell in Cities, ſave the Prieſts alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To whom the Kings aſsign'd a portion</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They therefore ſold no lands: then</hi> Ioſeph <hi>gave</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Others their ground and ſeed, but the fift thrave</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Pharoh's <hi>uſe reſerv'd and this did bring</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thanks from the ſubject, profit to the King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus the Almighty doth his ſervants bleſſe</l>
               <l>Giving to all their works a good ſucceſſe.</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:17029:55"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> the King's right hand, the people they</l>
               <l>As much in admiration of him, ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tis thou haſt ſav'd our lives, now let us find</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grace in thy ſight my Lord, ſo ſhalt thou bind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vs</hi> Pharohs <hi>ſervants, then a Law was made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> Ioſeph <hi>to this day, and</hi> Pharoh <hi>had</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fift of all their corn except alone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Prieſts that ſold no lands, did pay him none.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And happy <hi>Iſrael</hi> who in <hi>Goſhen</hi> dwelt</l>
               <l>Pleas'd with their new poſſeſſions, never felt</l>
               <l>The force of famine, nor the plague of want</l>
               <l>Was known among them, nothing there was ſcant,</l>
               <l>Bread for the man, and fodder for the beaſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> provided them; and they increaſt</l>
               <l>For they whom God doth bleſſe, ſhall multiply</l>
               <l>In ſpight of famine, or the tyranny</l>
               <l>O'th' worſt oppreſſors: all the harſh commands</l>
               <l>Of t'other <hi>Pharoh,</hi> nor the heavy hands</l>
               <l>Of their task-maſters, nor their loads laid on</l>
               <l>Could let at all their propagation;</l>
               <l>The hard preſt Grape yeelds moſt, and ſo the fire</l>
               <l>The greater load of woods it bears the higher</l>
               <l>The flames aſcend, as they oreburdned grow</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>Pharoh's</hi> hate doth but his weakneſſe ſhow.</l>
               <l>Such care had God, then, of his <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 16 18. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1 21.</note>As of his Church, 'gainſt which the gates of Hell</l>
               <l>Shall not prevayle: as death is made a gain</l>
               <l>To them that die in Chriſt, whoſe thought is pain,</l>
               <l>To worldlings minds, ſo here this plague befell</l>
               <l>Loſſe to the world, but gain to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who in their giv'n poſſeſſions joy'd, and there</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Old</hi> Iacob <hi>with his ſonnes liv'd ſev'nteen yeere.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:17029:55"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>So all the days that he on earth had liven</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By computation, ſevenſcore were and ſeven.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But when the time drew neere that he muſt die</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioſeph <hi>he call'd and underneath his thigh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<hi>So</hi> Abraham <hi>gave the oath) his hand did place</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſaid if in thy ſight I have found grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge.</hi> 24.2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bury me not in</hi> Egypt, <hi>let me ſleep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amongst my Fathers bones, that who ſo keep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My name or theirs in memory may be</l>
               <l>Pertakers of the ſelf-ſame obſequy.</l>
               <l>To this though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> plighted had his troth,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Iacob</hi> bound him further by an oath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe happy counted are in their deceaſe,</l>
               <l>Who to their fathers gather'd were in peace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> made this appear, who did interre</l>
               <l>None but good Kings in <hi>Davids</hi> ſepulcher</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So taught by</hi> Iacob, <hi>who in this being</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Worſhipt, his God, and turn'd him on his bed.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:17029:56"/>
            <head>THE BLESSING: OR, The eleventh Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. the 48.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>The thread of <hi>Iacob's</hi> life neer ſpun,</l>
               <l>He bleſſeth <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and his ſonnes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> was the ſecond born</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his brethrens hate, and ſcorn,</l>
               <l>Youngeſt of ten: yet was he bleſt,</l>
               <l>And more beloved then the reſt.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Ephraim</hi> heer the youngeſt lad,</l>
               <l>The bleſsings of the right hand had.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>A Greater love thoſe bleſſings more endears</l>
               <l>To us, which we have purchaſed with tears.</l>
               <l>Hence comes it, women love thoſe children moſt</l>
               <l>For whom they felt great'ſt pain: <hi>Iacob</hi> it coſt</l>
               <l>Many a zealous groan, ere he could gain</l>
               <l>The fruit of <hi>Rachels</hi> wombe, and long again</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:17029:56"/>
               <l>He wayl'd that loſſe with teares, as from the houre</l>
               <l>Her ſonne was borne, his love it ſelfe did ſhowre</l>
               <l>More upon his, than on his brethrens head,</l>
               <l>So for his loſſe he many tears ha'ing ſhed</l>
               <l>For him now found, he in an extaſie,</l>
               <l>As cloy'd with earthly joy, deſires to dye.</l>
               <l>The ſtrength of gladnes! were the world mine own,</l>
               <l>And I not wiſh it, ſure the bliſſe were none.</l>
               <l>But when the powres of the minde are bent</l>
               <l>Vpon one hope as 'twere the whole content</l>
               <l>Of mans deſire; and God ſhall thinke it fit</l>
               <l>To grant; no joy but heav'n is like to it.</l>
               <l>His wiſh on earth was, oh had <hi>Ioſeph</hi> liven!</l>
               <l>And that wiſh granted, now he wiſheth heaven,</l>
               <l>For which he doth prepare; his maſtred fleſh</l>
               <l>Yeelds to his conquering ſoule, which now afreſh</l>
               <l>Aſſaults the breach, weakeneſſe and age had made</l>
               <l>In his fraile body, thoſe old wals decaid,</l>
               <l>His ſpirit's halfe got forth, and doth foreſee</l>
               <l>By faith's cleere eye, heav'ns true felicity;</l>
               <l>Where all the fulneſſe doth of knowledge dwell,</l>
               <l>With which the Patriarch inſpir'd, doth tell</l>
               <l>His childrens following fates, and ere he dyes,</l>
               <l>Of all that muſt betide them, prophecies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But i'th meane time, conceive the news is quick,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And one brought</hi> Ioſeph <hi>word, his Fathers ſicke:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He therefore haſtning, brings along with him</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Sonnes,</hi> Manaſſes, <hi>and young</hi> Ephraim.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of whom, when</hi> Iacob <hi>heard, he rais'd his head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strengthning himſelfe, and ſate upon his bed:</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where thus to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> he his ſpeech began;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God did to me appeare in</hi> Canaan.</l>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:17029:57"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>At</hi> Luz, <hi>and bleſt me, promiſing increaſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To me, and to my ſeed, whoſe fruitfulneſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall fill the land, which for an habitation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They ſhall enjoy, and grow a mighty nation.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>As for thy ſonnes which were in</hi> Aegypt <hi>thine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before I came, thoſe I doe claime for mine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As</hi> Ruben <hi>are, and</hi> Symeon, <hi>they ſhall be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mine owne; thine after iſſue, all from thee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall take their names; and with their brethren ſhare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where they in their poſſeſsions ſetled are.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I from</hi> Padan <hi>came, my</hi> Rachel <hi>dyde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With me in</hi> Canaan <hi>by the high way ſide:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Twas ſhort of</hi> Ephrath, <hi>there I in the way</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Ephrath Bethelem, <hi>her bones did lay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But who are theſe ſaid</hi> Iſrael? <hi>for his eyes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Were weake and dimme with age;</hi> Ioſeph <hi>replyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe are my ſonnes, with whom God bleſt me here;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Iacob <hi>bade, and</hi> Ioſeph <hi>brought them neer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For him to bleſſe them, who firſt with a kiſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then claſping of their bodies cloſe to his,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Began the bleſsing: In that poſture</hi> Paul</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.9.</note>Rays'd <hi>Eutychus</hi> to life, who by his fall,</l>
               <l>Was doom'd to ſleepe for ever elſe: if there</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.20.</note>In the dead Prophets bones ſuch vertue were,</l>
               <l>To raiſe men from their graves, what vertue is</l>
               <l>Then in a living Patriarks holy kiſſe?</l>
               <l>Or if th' Apoſtles gave the ſpirit of grace,</l>
               <l>Where they impos'd their hands, ſure this imbrace</l>
               <l>Of a good man, ſome bleſſing brings along:</l>
               <l>'Tis a more full expreſſion then the tongue.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 22</note>Differing as deeds from words. <hi>Balaam</hi> muſt bleſſe</l>
               <l>Againſt his will: deſiring nothing leſſe.</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:17029:57"/>
               <l>But <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſſing, for its truth affords</l>
               <l>Apparant proofes, his deeds precede his words,</l>
               <l>Which with Gods mercies he began. I thought</l>
               <l>Nere to have ſeene thy face, but God hath brought</l>
               <l>Things to my moſt content, and hath decreed</l>
               <l>I ſhould not onely ſee thee, but thy ſeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Ephraim</hi> he preferd his right hand ſtayd</l>
               <l>Upon his head, the left athwart was laid</l>
               <l>On t'others, let none take offence to heare</l>
               <l>That <hi>Iacob</hi> bleſt his ſonnes, and croſt them there.</l>
               <l>Nor was't a thing of chance, but reade and ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He laid his hands acroſſe them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14</note> 
                  <hi>wittingly.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Though</hi> Ioſeph <hi>on his knees, preſents them quite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Contrary, and</hi> Manaſſes <hi>to the right</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hand offered firſt. So God 'mongſt</hi> Ieſſes <hi>ſonnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Choſe not for face or faire proportions,</l>
               <l>But what he ſaw within: he underſtands</l>
               <l>All hearts, and ſure he guided <hi>Iacobs</hi> hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who thus proceeds in bleſſing them, and ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The God from whom your Fathers never ſtraid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Abram, <hi>nor</hi> Iſack, <hi>God that me hath fed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All my life long till now, with daily bread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And the good Angell which ſuch care hath had,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me to redeeme from evils, bleſſe the lads;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be they by mine and</hi> Abrams <hi>ſacred name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> Iſacks <hi>cal'd the bleſsing of the ſame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As in <hi>Iohns</hi> viſion, thoſe that ſtamped were,</l>
               <l>And in their fronts the holy ſeale did beare,</l>
               <l>Were ſav'd from ruine, ſo God thoſe did bleſſe,</l>
               <l>That bore the Name of promiſe with increaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> pronounc'd the bleſſing well: ſaid he,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May they increaſe on earth, and multiply:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:17029:58"/>
               <l>So God firſt bleſt the world, when time began,</l>
               <l>Uſing thoſe words to new created man.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> Ioſeph <hi>not well pleas'd that</hi> Iacob <hi>laid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His right hand on the head of</hi> Ephraim, <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not ſo my Father, this the eldeſt is:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O be the choyſeſt of thy bleſsings his!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then to remove his reſolute hand, he tryes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But the attempt is vaine.</hi> Iacob <hi>denyes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(His mother could not cozen him, nor get</l>
               <l>The bleſſing, with another counterfeit,)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I know it well my Sonne, he alſo ſhall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A people be, ſaid he, and great withall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet ſhall his yonger brother him exceed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In greatneſſe; many nations from his ſeed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall be deriv'd: ſo bleſt he them that day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſaid, in thee ſhall</hi> Iſraell <hi>bleſſe, and ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In a Proverbiall wiſh; all good o'retake him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God like to</hi> Ephraim <hi>and</hi> Manaſſes, <hi>make him</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Happy and fruitfull; but in all that paſſes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still</hi> Ephraim <hi>he prefers before</hi> Manaſſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The bleſſing giv'n; the time which then drew nigh,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He antedating tels them, loe I dye:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet feare not, for with you ſhall God remaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And bring you to your Fathers land again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet one thing on thee more I will beſtow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Above thy brethren, which with ſword and bow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I wan, that I might adde it to thy right,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From the poſſeſsions of the</hi> Amorite.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:17029:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PROPHET: OR, The twelfth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 49.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> foreſees, and antedates</l>
               <l>His ſonnes returne, and following fates.</l>
               <l>Then having charg'd them to interre</l>
               <l>Him in his Fathers Sepulcher:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shilo's</hi> comming prophecies,</l>
               <l>Binds <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with an oath, and dyes.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>NOw</hi> Iacob <hi>haſtening to his owne, relates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calling his children to him, all their fates</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which his prophetique ſoule had then deſcryde,</l>
               <l>Should unto them in their laſt dayes betide.</l>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:17029:59"/>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Harken ye Sonnes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and gather</l>
               <l>Your ſelves (ſaid he) together to your Father.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>Ruben,</hi> my firſt borne Sonne unto my ſight</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Reuben.</note>Gives the beginning of my ſtrength and might.</l>
               <l>The pow'r of dignity and excellence,</l>
               <l>In him ſhould dwell, but that his foule offence</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Deprives him of it, therefore ſhall not he</l>
               <l>Excell, but as th'unconſtant wave ſhall be,</l>
               <l>For to his Fathers bed (an act moſt vilde,)</l>
               <l>Did he goe up, and he my Couch defild;</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <hi>Symeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in offence,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Symeon <hi>and</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</note>Have in their dwellings, ſwords of violence.</l>
               <l>Let not my ſoule into their ſecrets ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Nor let my honour e're united be</l>
               <l>To their aſſemblies, from whoſe angry breath,</l>
               <l>Iſſues revenge, with ruine arm'd, and death.</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Fierce was their anger, cruell was their wrath;</l>
               <l>Bloudy, revengefull, and accurſed both</l>
               <l>Therefore in <hi>Iacob</hi> they divided dwell,</l>
               <l>And I will ſcatter them in <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Judah.</note>But <hi>Iudah</hi> thee thy brethren ſhall commend,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Vnder thy hand, thine enemies necke ſhall bend;</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt prevaile, and ſtill a victor be,</l>
               <l>And all thy Fathers ſonnes ſhall bow to thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <hi>Iudah's</hi> a Lyons whelpe, ſo from the prey,</l>
               <l>My Sonne aſcends, ſo downe againe doth lay</l>
               <l>His conquering limbs, ſo doth th'old Lyon couch him</l>
               <l>To take his reſt, whiles none dares rouſe or touch him.</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The Scepter ſhall not, nor the Law goe from</l>
               <l>Between his feet, untill that <hi>Shiloe</hi> come:</l>
               <l>To whom a gathering ſhall of people be,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Whoſe Foale ſhall to the cluſter-bearing tree,</l>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:17029:59"/>
               <l>And his Aſſe Colt be bound unto the Vine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe cloaths in bloud of grapes are waſht, in wine</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> His garments ſteept, thence ſhall his inflam'd ſight</l>
               <l>Take tincture, and his teeth with milke grow white.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Zebulun</hi> at the Sea heaven ſhall reſt,<note place="margin">Zebulun</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> To him the Pilot flyes, with ſtormes diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>And findes a haven his ſhips may ſafely ride on,</l>
               <l>For loe his border ſhall be unto <hi>Zidon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like a ſtrong Aſſe is <hi>Iſſachar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſſachar.</note> between</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Two burdens couching downe, who having ſeen</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> That reſt was pleaſant, and the land was faire,</l>
               <l>His tributary ſhoulders bow'd to bear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> midſt his people, he a Iudge ſhall dwell,<note place="margin">Dan.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> And as one o'th Tribes of holy <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan</hi> ſhall be like a Serpent in the way,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> And like an Adder in the path ſhall lay</l>
               <l>Wayte to doe miſchiefe; ſlily, as they ſting</l>
               <l>The horſes heeles, till they their riders fling.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> But I O Lord have ever waited on</l>
               <l>The happy meanes of thy ſalvation.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gad</hi> by a troop ſhall be o'recome, but he</l>
               <l>Shall over them at laſt a victor be.<note place="margin">Gad.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/>
                  <hi>Aſhur</hi> his bread ſhall be o'th fat o'th field,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aſhurs</hi> cup ſhall royall dainties yeeld,<note place="margin">Aſhur.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Like to an Hinde let looſe is <hi>Nepthali,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neptha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.</note>
               </l>
               <l>He alſo ſhall a goodly ſpeaker be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
                  <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> a fruitfull bough, whoſe branches grow</l>
               <l>By a Well ſide, topping the walles:<note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> 'twas ſo</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> That <hi>David</hi> did the bleſſed man compare</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To trees that by the waters planted are.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/>
                  <hi>So envy ſhoots at vertue, ſome did hate him;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Archers ſorely griev'd him, and ſhot at him.</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:17029:60"/>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> But ſtill his bow abode in ſtrength, the armes</l>
               <l>Of his hands were made ſtrong, againſt all harmes,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Iacobs</hi> mighty God; all power is his,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> From thence ſhepheards ſtone of <hi>Iſraell</hi> is</l>
               <l>E'vn by thy Fathers God, whoſe help's on thee,</l>
               <l>And by th' Almighties bleſsing, which ſhall be</l>
               <l>Still on thy head, bleſsings from heav'n on high,</l>
               <l>And bleſsings from the deeps which lower lye.</l>
               <l>On thee ſhall bleſsings from all places come,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> The bleſsings of the breſt and of the wombe.</l>
               <l>The bleſsings of the Father hath prevaild.</l>
               <l>'Bove thoſe of my progenitors, and avail'd,</l>
               <l>More than their bleſsings, to the utmoſt bound</l>
               <l>O'th everlaſting hils, they ſhall abound</l>
               <l>On <hi>Ioſephs</hi> head, and on his crowne, that hated</l>
               <l>Of's brethren was, and from them ſeparated.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</note>Like to a ravening Wolfe, ſhall <hi>Benjamin</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'th morning to devoure the prey, begin;</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> And when at night he ceaſeth from his toyle,</l>
               <l>He ſhall take time then to divide the ſpoyle.</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> All theſe are <hi>Iſraels</hi> tribes, whom thus he bleſt,</l>
               <l>According to their bleſsings, from the leaſt</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Vnto the greateſt: then he charg'd them all</l>
               <l>To give him with his Fathers buriall.</l>
               <l>When I ſhall gathered to my people be,</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> In <hi>Ephrons</hi> field the <hi>Hittites</hi> bury me,</l>
               <l>I'th Cave that is at <hi>Macpelah,</hi> that lyes</l>
               <l>'Againſt <hi>Mamre,</hi> t'ath by <hi>Abram</hi> with a price,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ephrons</hi> field the <hi>Hittites</hi> purchas'd bin,</l>
               <l>As a poſſeſsion for to bury in.</l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> His ſacred bones, with <hi>Sarahs</hi> were laid there,</l>
               <l>There <hi>Iſack</hi> and <hi>Rebeckah</hi> buried were.</l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:17029:60"/>
               <l>There I my <hi>Leah</hi> laid, and there would I</l>
               <l>In the ſame cave with thoſe lov'd aſhes lie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That as one fleſh and bloud we living were,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In like alliance in the Sepulcher</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We might conſume united thus in death</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/>
                  <hi>The field and cave was bought o'th ſonnes of</hi> Heth.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This having ſaid, thus ending his commands</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Unto his ſonnes, then he withdrew his hands</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And feet, yeilding his ghoſt up into bed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And was unto his Fathers gathered.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:17029:61"/>
            <head>THE FVNERALL: OR, The thirteenth Chapter of <hi>Joſeph. GEN. 50.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his brethren all,</l>
               <l>Attend their Fathers funerall.</l>
               <l>They humble ſupplyants ſhew their fears,</l>
               <l>To him who comforts them and chears</l>
               <l>Their heavy ſpirits: all their rage,</l>
               <l>Forgot, in peace, and full of age,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Egypt</hi> he lamented dies</l>
               <l>And there embalm'd and coffind lies.</l>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IAcob,</hi> his Fathers imitates in death</l>
               <l>And in a bleſſing ſpent his lateſt breath;</l>
               <l>Sure good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion for 't from God was given,</l>
               <l>For he no ſooner ended but to Heaven</l>
               <l>His ſoule was carried; as if that the laſt</l>
               <l>Were of his buſineſſe here on earth, which paſt</l>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:17029:61"/>
               <l>He leaves it: having then no more to do,</l>
               <l>And on his journey forwards ſets, when lo</l>
               <l>As the <hi>Epheſians</hi> loath to part with <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To the ſhip ſides with grief they brought him all;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Iacob's</hi> ſonnes their ſpirits overcome,</l>
               <l>With ſorrow; left a while their earthly home</l>
               <l>And as men ſtruck with the ſame fate; they lay</l>
               <l>As dead as he; they ſure brought on his way</l>
               <l>Their fathers ſoul towards heav'n, for long 'twas e're</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> recovered ſtrength to ſhed a tear,</l>
               <l>Lumpiſh as lead: i'th' fire which melted powres</l>
               <l>And flowes about, he lay, but now he ſhowres</l>
               <l>His dead trance broken, on his Fathers face</l>
               <l>A floud of tears, then with a ſad embrace</l>
               <l>He eſcaps his grief, ſuch ſtreams of ſorrows fall</l>
               <l>As if his moyſture were diſſolved all</l>
               <l>Into his eyes: then with a pious kiſſe</l>
               <l>Strives to ſupply the breathleſſe trunk with his</l>
               <l>Which he in ſighing vents: but ſeeing his breath</l>
               <l>Vain as his wiſhes to recall from death;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To the Phyſicians he converts it, whom</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(To fit the body for a forreign tomb)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He gives command that they embalm it well</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So they perform'd their charge, on</hi> Iſraell</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then after forty dayes were fully past,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So long the dayes of men embalmed last.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The lamentation for him ſure was ſore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th'</hi> Egyptians <hi>they bewayle him ſeventy more.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But when the times of mourning ended were</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Ceremoniall rites, he drawing nere</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Pharohs <hi>houſe, requests if I have found</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grace in your ſight's, thus tell him,</hi> Ioſeph's <hi>bound,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:17029:62"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>To 's father by an oath, he may be laid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ith' ſepulcher, he for himſelfe had made</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Canaan. <hi>Let me therefore go I pray</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>According to my vow, that I may lay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My father in his grave: I ſhall remayn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But few dayes abſent, e're I come again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharoh</hi> that never any ſuit deny'de,</l>
               <l>His Favourite <hi>Ioſeph</hi> moved for, thus replyde:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Go up in peace thou haſt free leave, and there</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bury thy father, as he made thee ſweare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> Ioſeph <hi>with the ſervants of the King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Went with his fathers coarſe; with tears they bring</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him to his grave, the Elders of the Land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And of the Court, his houſe, his brethren, and</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His fathers houſe; behind they left alone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their ſheep, their cattell, and their little ones.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As from ſome Town, fire, or the hand of fate,</l>
               <l>Hath clean demoliſh't and made deſolate,</l>
               <l>The grieved Citizens march to forſake,</l>
               <l>Her ruin'd walls, ſuch lamentations make</l>
               <l>The ſad <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and their tears let fall</l>
               <l>As had old <hi>Iacob</hi> father been to all.</l>
               <l>Fierce is the battle when the dreadfull ſound</l>
               <l>Of groans and ſhreeks of men departing, drown'd</l>
               <l>The Drum and Trumpet, ſuch the wofull voice</l>
               <l>Of the ſad mourners, overcame the noiſe</l>
               <l>Of all the Chariot wheels, the trampling ſteeds,</l>
               <l>Though they were many, ſuch ſound proceeds,</l>
               <l>From their high ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> griefs, men ſcarce could hear,</l>
               <l>Tears fild their eyes, their cryes fild ev'ry ear.</l>
               <l>Their cryes were ſtrong and lowd enought t'have given</l>
               <l>A ſummons back from any place, but heaven,</l>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:17029:62"/>
               <l>Or the deep pit of Hell, where ſhreeks and howles,</l>
               <l>Are lowder of the there tormented ſoules.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Goren Arad,</hi> deafneſſe ſtrikes their ears</l>
               <l>Wonder their eyes, to ſee ſalt ſhowres of tears</l>
               <l>Adde ſtreams to <hi>Iordan,</hi> which ſeven days oreflow'd</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> mourning, whilſt he there aboad.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cananites</hi> and dwellers round about</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Take pitious notice of it, ſuch a ſhout</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of ſorrow, nere was heard there, therefore they</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thence nam'd it</hi> Abel Miſraim, to this day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>So the performance anſwer d his command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſonnes have carried him into the land</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Canaan, <hi>and there laid him in the Vault</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Machpelah, <hi>which with the field was bought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> Abraham, <hi>of the</hi> Hittite, Ephron <hi>all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Intended for a place of buriall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now a new, having hallowed the Cave</l>
               <l>Adding the ſacred body to the grave,</l>
               <l>Of his forefathers, they tow'rds <hi>Egypt</hi> hye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> his brethren, and his company.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One miſchief ſeldome comes alone; the loſſe</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his ſonnes, hath yet a croſſe</l>
               <l>Adds terour to their grief ſhould <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be</l>
               <l>Mindfull of their old grudge, and miſery</l>
               <l>He had ſuſtain'd, and now the mourning days</l>
               <l>For their dead Father ended, he might rayſe</l>
               <l>His ſpirit to revenge, but that fears done</l>
               <l>They find him <hi>Iſraels</hi> not rough <hi>Eſau's</hi> ſonne.</l>
               <l>For when they joyntly had advis'd and ſent,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an attoning complement,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> Iacobs <hi>honour'd name, this do we ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By his command'ment now forgive I pray,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:17029:63"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>The treſpaſſe of thy brethren, and their ſinne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherby thou haſt ſo ill rewarded bin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſervants of thy Fathers God we are</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Forgive our treſpaſſe then we pray thee, ſpare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Further entreaties anſwer'd he, in tears</l>
               <l>Seeking to drown or waſh away their fears.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When altogether they thus ſpeaking kneel'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We are thy ſervants, uſe us thou wilt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To whom thus</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>fear not (makes reply)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not ſo w'are all Gods ſervants, am not I</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnder him too, and when yee ſought my blood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did not he then convert it all to good?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That he as 'tis this day might it contrive,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I much people might preſerve alive,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fear nothing then, theſe words his tears aſſures</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will a comfort be to you, and yours,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo prevail'd theſe ſpeeche's that they gate</l>
               <l>His love now firmer then their former hate,</l>
               <l>How bleſt a ſight when brethren thus agree?</l>
               <l>A happy change ends <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Comedy.</l>
               <l>This makes a peacefull <hi>exit,</hi> true content</l>
               <l>Crowns their remayning days, in <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpent.</l>
               <l>No more tormented now with griefs or fears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till</hi> Ioſeph <hi>having liv'd an hundred years</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ten, perceiving that the time drew nigh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calling his brethren, told them he muſt die,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſonnes were preſent,</hi> Ephraims <hi>ſeed he ſees</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto the third deſcent, and on the knees</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Manaſſes <hi>grandchild holds, a joy to bleſſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Patriarch party to Gods promiſes.</l>
               <l>He kept Gods ſecrets living, now he dyes</l>
               <l>Which leave make ſome known he prophecies.</l>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:17029:63"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>God will his brethren viſit, and recall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Them from this place, to that land wherewithall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Abraham <hi>and to</hi> Iſack <hi>heretofore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> Iacob <hi>he to bleſſe their of-ſpring ſwore.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>This ſaid, he miniſtred his Fathers oath</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto his children, and gave charge to both,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He might be buried by his Fathers ſide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An hundred then and ten yeers old he dy'de.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So much bewail'd, that my unskilfull pen,</l>
               <l>Might by their griefes inſpir'd, force tears from men</l>
               <l>Of this laſt age, whoſe flinty hearts deny,</l>
               <l>Should all the world, themſelves excepted dye,</l>
               <l>To weep: unleſſe for want of company.</l>
               <l>Should they but witneſſe here, what ſhowrs were ſpent,</l>
               <l>Rivers of melted ſorrowes to lament</l>
               <l>This Hearſe; as when black clowds threat drops of raine,</l>
               <l>Strong ſympathy from ſtony wals doth draigne</l>
               <l>Diſtilling moyſture, all thoſe weeping eyes</l>
               <l>Would force from their hard hearts like pitty riſe,</l>
               <l>Should they but heare their waylings as they went</l>
               <l>To <hi>Canaan</hi> with his bones; but what was meant</l>
               <l>Here for a Comicke ſtory, leſt that I</l>
               <l>By this relation, make a tragedy.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Embalm'd in</hi> Egypt, <hi>I ſhall let him reſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fitted with coſtly odour, for his Cheſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
